<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
<channel>
<title><![CDATA[Planet Python francophone]]></title>
<description><![CDATA[News Python francophones]]></description>
<link>http://www.afpy.org/planet/</link>
<language>en</language>
<copyright>Copyright 2008, Atomisator</copyright>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2008 00:15:05 +0200</pubDate>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2008 00:15:05 +0200</lastBuildDate>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] The Configuration Management Problem]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9863?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9863?vid=download" />
<p>Today I felt like summing up my opinion on a topic that was discussed this year on
the Python mailing lists, at PyCon-FR, at EuroPython and EuroSciPy... packaging
software! Let us discuss the two main use cases.</p>
<p>The first use case is to maintain computer systems in production. A trait of
production systems, is that they can not afford failures and are often deployed
on a large scale. It leaves little room for manually fixing problems. Either
the installation process works or the system fails. Reaching that level of
quality takes a lot of work.</p>
<p>The second use case is to facilitate the life of software developers and computer
users by making it easy for them to give a try to new pieces of software without
much work.</p>
<p>The first use case <em>has</em> to be addressed as a <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Configuration_management">configuration management</a>
problem. There is no way around it. The best way I know of managing the
configuration of a computer system is called <a class="reference" href="http://www.debian.org/">Debian</a>. Its package format and its
tool chain provide a very extensive and efficient set of features for system
development and maintenance. Of course it is not perfect and there are missing
bits and open issues that could be tackled, like the dependencies between
hardware and software. For example, nothing will prevent you from installing on
your Debian system a version of a driver that conflicts with the version of the
chip found in your hardware. That problem could be solved, but I do not think
the Debian project is there yet and I do not count it as a reason to reject
Debian since I have not seen any other competitor at the level as Debian.</p>
<p>The second use case is kind of a trap, for it concerns most computer users and
most of those users are either convinced the first use case has nothing in
common with their problem or convinced that the solution is easy and requires
little work.</p>
<p>The situation is made more complicated by the fact that most of those users
never had the chance to use a system with proper package management tools. They
simply do not know the difference and do not feel like they are <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/blogentry/9861">missing</a> when
using their system-that-comes-with-a-windowing-system-included.</p>
<p>Since many software developers have never had to maintain computer systems in
production (often considered a lower sysadmin job) and never developed packages
for computer systems that are maintained in production, they tend to think that
the operating system and their software are perfectly decoupled. They have no
problem trying to create a new layer on top of existing operating systems and
transforming an operating system issue (managing software installation) into a
programming langage issue (see CPAN, Python eggs and so many others).</p>
<p>Creating a sub-system specific to a language and hosting it on an operating
system works well as long as the language boundary is not crossed and there is
no competition between the sub-system and the system itself. In the Python
world, distutils, setuptools, eggs and the like more or less work with pure
Python code. They create a square wheel that was made round years ago by
dpkg+apt-get and others, but they help a lot of their users do something they
would not know how to do another way.</p>
<p>A wall is quickly hit though, as the approach becoms overly complex as soon as
they try to depend on things that do not belong to their Python sub-system. What
if your application needs a database? What if your application needs to link to
libraries? What if your application needs to reuse data from or provide data to
other applications? What if your application needs to work on different
architectures?</p>
<p>The software developers that never had to maintain computer systems in
production wish these tasks were easy. Unfortunately they are not easy and cannot be. As I said, there is no way around configuration management for the one
who wants a stable system. Configuration management requires both project
management work and software development work. One can have a system where
packaging software is less work, but that comes at the price of stability and
reduced functionnality and ease of maintenance.</p>
<p>Since none of the two use cases will disappear any time soon, the only solution
to the problem is to share as much data as possible between the different tools
and let each one decide how to install software on his computer system.</p>
<p>Some links to continue your readings on the same topic:</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li><a class="reference" href="http://cournape.wordpress.com/2009/05/25/the-every-linux-distribution-should-have-the-same-package-manager-fallacy/">The every Linux distribution should have the same package manager fallacy</a> by D. Cournapeau</li>
<li><a class="reference" href="http://cournape.wordpress.com/2009/04/01/python-packaging-a-few-observations-cabal-for-a-solution/">Python Packaging: a few observations and a cabal for a solution</a> by D. Cournapeau</li>
<li><a class="reference" href="http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/24/words-on-distribute-distutils-pep-376-pep-386-pep-345/">Words on distribute, distutils and PEP 376, 386, 345</a> by Tarek Ziadé</li>
</ul><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/viYkOez-KvY/9579">[logilab] EuroPython 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/HiUtO6H72hg/9860]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-31 19:24:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] Looking for a Windows Package Manager]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9862?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9862?vid=download" />
<p>As said in a previous <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/blogentry/9860">article</a>, I am convinced that part of the motivation for
making package sub-systems like the Python one, which includes distutils,
setuptools, etc, is that Windows users and Mac users never had the chance to use
a tool that properly manages the configuration of their computer system. They
just do not know what it would be like if they had at least a good <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Package_management_system">package
management system</a> and do not miss it in their daily work.</p>
<p>I looked for Windows package managers that claim to provide features similar to
Debian's dpkg+apt-get and here is what I found in alphabetical order.</p>
<div class="section" id="appsnap">
<h3><a>AppSnap</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://appsnap.genotrance.com/">AppSnap</a> is written in Python and uses wxPython, PyCurl and PyYAML. It is
packaged using Py2Exe, compressed with UPX and installed using NSIS.</p>
<p>It has not seen activity in the svn or on its blog since the end of 2008.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="appupdater">
<h3><a>Appupdater</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://www.nabber.org/projects/appupdater/">Appupdater</a> provides functionality similar to apt-get or yum. It automates the
process of installing and maintaining up to date versions of programs. It claims
to be fully customizable and is licensed under the GPL.</p>
<p>It seems under active development at SourceForge.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="qwinapt">
<h3><a>QWinApt</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/qwinapt/">QWinApt</a> is a <a class="reference" href="http://www.nongnu.org/synaptic/">Synaptic</a> clone written in C# that has not evolved since september 2007.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="winaptic">
<h3><a>WinAptic</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/winaptic/">WinAptic</a> is another <a class="reference" href="http://www.nongnu.org/synaptic/">Synaptic</a> clone written this time in Pascal that has not evolved since
the end of 2007.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="win-get">
<h3><a>Win-Get</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://windows-get.sourceforge.net/">Win-get</a> is an automated install system and software repository for Microsoft
Windows. It is similar to apt-get: it connects to a link repository, finds an
application and downloads it before performing the installation routine (silent
or standard) and deleting the install file.</p>
<p>It is written in pascal and is set up as a SourceForge project, but not much has
been done lately.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="winlibre">
<h3><a>WinLibre</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://www.winlibre.com/en/">WinLibre</a> is a Windows free software distribution that provides a repository of
packages and a tool to automate and simplify their installation.</p>
<p>WinLibre was selected for Google Summer of Code 2009.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="zeroinstall">
<h3><a>ZeroInstall</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://0install.net/">ZeroInstall</a> started as a &quot;non-admin&quot; package manager for Linux distributions and
is now extending its reach to <a class="reference" href="http://0install.net/install-windows.html">work on windows</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="conclusion">
<h3><a>Conclusion</a></h3>
<p>I have not used any of these tools, the above is just the result of some time
spent searching the web.</p>
<p>A more limited approach is to notify the user of the newer versions:</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li><a class="reference" href="http://www.app-get.com/">App-Get</a> will show you a list of your installed Applications. When an update
is available for one of them, it will highlighted and you will be able to
update the specific applications in seconds.</li>
</ul>
<ul class="simple">
<li><a class="reference" href="http://puchisoft.com/GetIt/">GetIt</a> is not an application-getter/installer. When you want to install a
program, you can look it up in GetIt to choose which program to install from a
master list of all programs made available by the various apt-get clones.</li>
</ul>
<p>The appupdater project also <a class="reference" href="http://www.nabber.org/projects/appupdater/compare.html">compares</a> itself to the programs automating the
installation of software on Windows.</p>
<p>Some columists expect the creation of <a class="reference" href="http://www.maximumpc.com/article/columns/murphys_law_it_time_opensource_app_store">application stores</a> replicating the iPhone
one.</p>
<p>I once read about a project to get the Windows kernel into the Debian
distribution, but can not find any trace of it... Remember that Debian is <a class="reference" href="http://www.debian.org/ports/">not
limited</a> to the Linux kernel, so why not think about an very improbable
<tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">apt-get</span> <span class="pre">install</span> <span class="pre">windows-vista</span></tt> ?</p>
</div>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/9jw9lh1-DdE/9861]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-31 16:20:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] EuroSciPy'09 (part 1/2): The Need For Speed]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9852?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9852?vid=download" />
<p>The <a class="reference" href="http://www.euroscipy.org/">EuroSciPy2009</a> conference was held in Leipzig at the end of July and was
sponsored by Logilab and other companies. It started with three talks about speed.</p>
<div class="section" id="starving-cpus">
<h3><a>Starving CPUs</a></h3>
<p>In his keynote, Fransesc Alted talked about <a class="reference" href="http://www.euroscipy.org/presentations/slides/slides_alted.pdf">starving CPUs</a>. Thirty years back,
memory and CPU frequencies where about the same. Memory speed kept up for about
ten years with the evolution of CPU speed before falling behind. Nowadays,
memory is about a hundred times slower than the cache which is itself about
twenty times slower than the CPU. The direct consequence is that CPUs are
starving and spend many clock cycles waiting for data to process.</p>
<p>In order to improve the performance of programs, it is now required to know
about the multiple layers of computer memory, from disk storage to CPU. The
common architecture will soon count six levels: mechanical disk, solid state
disk, ram, cache level 3, cache level 2, cache level 1.</p>
<p>Using optimized array operations, taking striding into account, processing data
blocks of the right size and using compression to diminish the amount of data
that is transfered from one layer to the next are four techniques that go a long
way on the road to high performance. Compression algorithms like Blosc increase
throughput for they strike the right balance between being fast and providing
good compression ratios. Blosc compression will soon be available in <a class="reference" href="http://www.pytables.org/">PyTables</a>.</p>
<p>Fransesc also mentions the <a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/numexpr/">numexpr</a> extension to <a class="reference" href="http://numpy.scipy.org/">numpy</a>, and its combination with
PyTables named tables.Expr, that nicely and easily accelerates the computation
of some expressions involving numpy arrays. In his list of references, Fransesc
cites Ulrich Drepper article <a class="reference" href="http://people.redhat.com/drepper/cpumemory.pdf">What every programmer should know about memory</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="using-pypy-s-jit-for-science">
<h3><a>Using PyPy's JIT for science</a></h3>
<p>Maciej Fijalkowski started his talk with a general presentation of the <a class="reference" href="http://pypy.org/">PyPy</a>
framework. One uses PyPy to describe an interpreter in RPython, then generate
the actual interpreter code and its JIT.</p>
<p>Since <a class="reference" href="http://pypy.org/">PyPy</a> is has become more of a framework to write interpreters than a
reimplementation of Python in Python, I suggested to change its misleading name to
something like <cite>gcgc the Generic Compiler for Generating Compilers</cite>. Maciej
answered that there are discussions on the mailing list to split the project in
two and make the implementation of the Python interpreter distinct from the GcGc
framework.</p>
<p>Maciej then focused his <a class="reference" href="http://www.euroscipy.org/presentations/slides/slides_fijalkowski.pdf">talk</a> on his recent effort to rewrite in RPython the part
of <a class="reference" href="http://numpy.scipy.org/">numpy</a> that exposes the underlying C library to Python. He says the benefits
of using PyPy's JIT to speedup that wrapping layer are already visible. He has
<a class="reference" href="http://morepypy.blogspot.com/2009/07/pypy-numeric-experiments.html">details</a> on the PyPy blog. Gaël Varoquaux added that David Cournapeau has
started working on making the C/Python split in numpy cleaner, which would
further ease the job of rewriting it in RPython.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="crosstwine-linker">
<h3><a>CrossTwine Linker</a></h3>
<p>Damien Diederen talked about his <a class="reference" href="http://www.euroscipy.org/presentations/slides/slides_diederen.pdf">work</a> on <a class="reference" href="http://crosstwine.com/linker/">CrossTwine Linker</a> and compared it
with the many projects that are actively attacking the problem of speed that
dynamic and interpreted languages have been dragging along for years. <a class="reference" href="http://www.parrot.org/">Parrot</a>
tries to be the über virtual machine. <a class="reference" href="http://psyco.sourceforge.net/">Psyco</a> offers very nice acceleration, but
currently only on 32bits system. <a class="reference" href="http://pypy.org/">PyPy</a> might be what he calls the Right
Approach, but still needs a lot of work. Jython and IronPython modify the
language a bit but benefit from the qualities of the <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JVM">JVM</a> or the <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Language_Runtime">CLR</a>. <a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/unladen-swallow/">Unladen
Swallow</a> is probably the one that's most similar to CrossTwine.</p>
<p>CrossTwine considers CPython as a library and uses a set of C++ classes to
generate efficient interpreters that make calls to CPython's
internals. CrossTwine is a tool that helps improving performance by
hand-replacing some code paths with very efficient code that does the same
operations but bypasses the interpreter and its overhead. An interpreter built
with CrossTwine can be viewed as a JIT'ed branch of the official Python
interpreter that should be feature-compatible (and bug-compatible) with CPython.
Damien calls he approach &quot;punching holes in C substrate to get more speed&quot; and
says it could probably be combined with Psyco for even better results.</p>
<p>CrossTwine works on 64bit systems, but it is not (yet?) free software. It
focuses on some use cases to greatly improve speed and is not to be considered a
general purpose interpreter able to make any Python code faster.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="more-readings">
<h3><a>More readings</a></h3>
<p><a class="reference" href="http://cython.org/">Cython</a> is a language that makes writing C extensions for the Python language as
easy as Python itself. It replaces the older <a class="reference" href="http://www.cosc.canterbury.ac.nz/greg.ewing/python/Pyrex/">Pyrex</a>.</p>
<p>The <a class="reference" href="http://conference.scipy.org/proceedings/SciPy2008/">SciPy2008</a> conference had at least two papers talking about speeding Python:
<a class="reference" href="http://conference.scipy.org/proceedings/SciPy2008/paper_16/">Converting Python Functions to Dynamically Compiled C</a> and
<a class="reference" href="http://conference.scipy.org/proceedings/SciPy2008/paper_17/">unPython: Converting Python Numerical Programs into C</a>.</p>
<p>David Beazley gave a very interesting talk at PyCon2009 about the effects of the
<a class="reference" href="http://www.dabeaz.com/python/GIL.pdf">GIL on multicore</a> machines.</p>
<p>I will continue my report on the conference with the second part titled
&quot;Applications And Open Questions&quot;.</p>
</div><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/viYkOez-KvY/9579">[logilab] EuroPython 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/KOOCPO5FNf8/9853]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-30 13:21:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[carlchenet] Pro Git]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[La prise en main de Git par des programmeurs qui utilisaient auparavant des gestionnaires de sources centralisés est souvent difficile. Comment démarrer ? Comment s&#8217;organiser ? Comment gérer les rapports entre la version locale et la version sur le serveur de gestionnaire de sources ? Pourquoi les branches ? Comment travailler avec ?
Pour répondre à [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=carlchenet.wordpress.com&blog=7722010&post=78&subd=carlchenet&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://carlchenet.wordpress.com/2009/07/29/pro-git/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-29 18:57:02</pubDate>
    <category>debian-fr</category>
    <category>python</category>
    <category>git</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] Sparkles everywhere, CubicWeb gets fizzy]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9845?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9845?vid=download" />
<p>Last week, we finally took a few days to dive into <a class="reference" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/">SPARQL</a> in
order to transform any CubicWeb application into a potential
SPARQL endpoint.</p>
<p>The first step was to get a parser. Fortunately
the w3c provides a <a class="reference" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/#grammar">grammar</a> definition and around 200 test
cases. There was a few interesting options around there: we
tried to reuse <a class="reference" href="http://www.rdflib.net/">rdflib</a>, <a class="reference" href="http://librdf.org/rasqal/">rasqal</a>, the <cite>sparql.g</cite> version
designed for <cite>antlr3</cite> and <a class="reference" href="http://simpleparse.sourceforge.net/">SimpleParse</a> but after two days of
work, we had nothing that worked well enough. We decided it was
not worth it and switched to <a class="reference" href="http://theory.stanford.edu/~amitp/yapps/">yapps</a> since we knew yapps and rql
already had a dependency on it.</p>
<p>Maybe we'll consider changing the parser at some point later but
the priority was to get something working as soon as we could and
we finally came up with a version of <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/project/fyzz">fyzz</a> passing 90% of the
W3C test suite (of course, there might be some false positives).</p>
<p>Fyzz parses the SPARQL query and generates something we decided to call an
AST although it's still a bit rough for now. Fyzz understands simple triples,
distincts, limits, offsets and other basic functionalities.</p>
<p>Please note that <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/project/fyzz">fyzz</a> is <strong>totally independent of cubicweb</strong> and it can
be reused by any project.</p>
<p>Here's an example of how to use fyzz:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">fyzz.yappsparser</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">parse</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">ast</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">parse</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;&quot;&quot;PREFIX doap: &lt;http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#&gt;</span>
<span class="s">... SELECT ?project ?name WHERE {</span>
<span class="s">...    ?project a doap:Project;</span>
<span class="s">...         doap:name ?name.</span>
<span class="s">... }</span>
<span class="s">... ORDER BY ?name LIMIT 5 OFFSET 10</span>
<span class="s">... &quot;&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">ast</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">selected</span>
<span class="p">[</span><span class="n">SparqlVar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'project'</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">SparqlVar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'name'</span><span class="p">)]</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">ast</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">prefixes</span>
<span class="p">{</span><span class="s">'doap'</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s">'http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#'</span><span class="p">}</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">ast</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">orderby</span>
<span class="p">[(</span><span class="n">SparqlVar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'name'</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="s">'asc'</span><span class="p">)]</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">ast</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">limit</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ast</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">offset</span>
<span class="mf">5</span> <span class="mf">10</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">ast</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">where</span>
<span class="p">[(</span><span class="n">SparqlVar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'project'</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">''</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'a'</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'Project'</span><span class="p">)),</span>
 <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">SparqlVar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'project'</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'name'</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">SparqlVar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'name'</span><span class="p">))]</span>
</pre></div>
<p>This AST is then processed and transformed into a RQL query which
can finally be processed by CubicWeb directly.</p>
<p>Here's what can be done in <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">cubicweb-ctl</span> <span class="pre">shell</span></tt> session (of course,
this can also be done in the web application) of our forge
cube:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">cubicweb.spa2rql</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">Sparql2rqlTranslator</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">query</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">&quot;&quot;&quot;PREFIX doap: &lt;http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#&gt;</span>
<span class="s">... SELECT ?project ?name WHERE {</span>
<span class="s">...    ?project a doap:Project;</span>
<span class="s">...         doap:name ?name.</span>
<span class="s">... }</span>
<span class="s">... ORDER BY ?name LIMIT 5 OFFSET 10</span>
<span class="s">... &quot;&quot;&quot;</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">qinfo</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">translator</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">translate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">query</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">rql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">args</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">qinfo</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">finalize</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">rql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">args</span>
<span class="n">Any</span> <span class="n">PROJECT</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">NAME</span> <span class="n">ORDERBY</span> <span class="n">NAME</span> <span class="n">ASC</span> <span class="n">LIMIT</span> <span class="mf">5</span> <span class="n">OFFSET</span> <span class="mf">10</span> <span class="n">WHERE</span> <span class="n">PROJECT</span> <span class="n">name</span> <span class="n">NAME</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">PROJECT</span> <span class="ow">is</span> <span class="n">Project</span> <span class="p">{}</span>
</pre></div>
<p>From the above example, we can notice two things. First, for
cubicweb to understand the <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">doap</span></tt> namespace, we have to
declare the correspondance between the standard <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">doap</span></tt> vocabulary
and our internal schema, this is done with <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">yams.xy</span></tt>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">yams</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">xy</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">xy</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">register_prefix</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'doap'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">xy</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">add_equivalence</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'Project'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'doap:Project'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">xy</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">add_equivalence</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'Project name'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'doap:Project doap:name'</span><span class="p">)</span>
</pre></div>
<p>Secondly, for now, we notice that the case is not preserved during the
transformation : <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">?project</span></tt> becomes <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">PROJECT</span></tt> in the rql query. This
is probably something that we'll need to tackle quickly.</p>
<p>We've also add a few views in CubicWeb to wrap that and it will
be available in the upcoming version <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/project/cubicweb/3.4.0">3.4.0</a> and is already
available through our pulic mercurial <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/cgi-bin/hgwebdir.cgi/cubicweb/">repository</a>.</p>
<p>The door is now open, the path is still long, stay tuned !</p>
<p><em>image under</em> <a class="reference" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/deed.en_GB">creative commons</a> <em>by</em> <a class="reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/beger/">beger</a> (<a class="reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/beger/2335652487/">original</a>)</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/yAy0KLWb-Vc/9827">[logilab] Logilab at OSCON 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/RItpr_z3C_A/344822]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-29 15:53:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] CubicWeb for DBPedia and OpenLibrary at PyConFr'09]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.cubicweb.org/image/343602?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.cubicweb.org/image/343602?vid=download" />
<p>I presented CubicWeb at the <a class="reference" href="http://www.pycon.fr/">French Python Conference</a> held in Paris last week-end. Check out the <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.fr/publications/pyconfr2009-cubicweb">slides</a> and the <a class="reference" href="http://video.pycon.fr/videos/free/81/">video</a>. See also my recent post <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/blogentry/9138">Fetching book descriptions and covers</a> on logilab.org.</p>
<p>The code used during the demo uses the brand new <em>RangeFacet</em>, <em>DateRangeFacet</em> and <em>HasRelationFacet</em> brought by CubicWeb 3.3 and is available in the cubes <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/project/cubicweb-dbpedia">dbpedia</a> and <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/project/cubicweb-book">book</a>. We will put the demos online in a couple weeks once we get a new server with more horsepower. Help would be welcome to set them up as Amazon EC2 or Eucalyptus instances.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/pavEfIaZcmY/9209">[logilab] Nous allons à PyConFr 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/viYkOez-KvY/9579">[logilab] EuroPython 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/8dXfwGMfuLU/9138">[logilab] Fetching book descriptions and covers</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/post/2009/06/01/Compte-Rendu-Pycon-FR-2009">[nsteinmetz] Compte Rendu Pycon-FR 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/CvQCQ7Rp5bQ/343598]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-29 15:42:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9631?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9631?vid=download" />
<p>I am pleased to announce that <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org">CubicWeb</a> will be presented during a BayPIGgies meeting that will exceptionally take place in the <a class="reference" href="http://en.oreilly.com/oscon2009/public/schedule/detail/10349">OSCON</a> conference building as the closing event of the Bird of Feathers on July 23rd at 8pm.</p>
<p>Joins us to get to know more about <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org">CubicWeb</a>.</p>
<p>Read the <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/blogentry/9827">report</a>.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/GA-4QEbeUf0/9630">[logilab] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/yAy0KLWb-Vc/9827">[logilab] Logilab at OSCON 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/o56b5TqtoRs/344425">[cubicweb] Graphing version progress</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/pavEfIaZcmY/9209">[logilab] Nous allons à PyConFr 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/nct5PaugpYM/9152">[logilab] Almost reached 1000 tickets</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/3yWbpUOUNKc/9097">[logilab] iclassmethod decorator to define both a class and an instance method in one go</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/TTSEwjKo2L0/8815">[logilab] Venez nous rendre visite à Solution Linux 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/zi7_LkueHLA/344573]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-28 18:35:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] Logilab at OSCON 2009]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://assets.en.oreilly.com/1/event/27/oscon2009_oscon_11_years.gif" class="align-right" src="http://assets.en.oreilly.com/1/event/27/oscon2009_oscon_11_years.gif" />
<p><a class="reference" href="http://en.oreilly.com/oscon2009">OSCON</a>, Open Source CONvention, takes place every year and promotes Open Source for technology.
It is one of the meeting hubs for the growing open source community. This was the occasion for us
to learn about new projects and to present <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org">CubicWeb</a> during a <a class="reference" href="http://baypiggies.net/">BAYPIGgies</a> meeting hosted by
OSCON.</p>
<img align="left" alt="http://www.openlina.com/templates/rhuk_milkyway/images/header_red_left.png" class="align-left" src="http://www.openlina.com/templates/rhuk_milkyway/images/header_red_left.png" />
<p>I had the chance to talk with some of the folks working at OpenLina where they presented <a class="reference" href="http://www.openlina.com/">LINA</a>.
<a class="reference" href="http://www.openlina.com/">LINA</a> is a thin virtual layer that enables developers to write and compile code using ordinary Linux tools, then package that code into a single executable that runs on a variety of operating systems. <a class="reference" href="http://www.openlina.com/">LINA</a> runs invisibly in the background, enabling the user to install and run LINAfied Linux applications as if they were native to that user's operating system.
They were curious about CubicWeb and took as a challenge to package it with <a class="reference" href="http://www.openlina.com/">LINA</a>... maybe soon on <a class="reference" href="http://www.openlina.com/index.php/users/applications-for-lina/the-lina-exchange">LINA's applications list</a>.</p>
<p>Two open sources projects catched my attention as potential semantic data publishers. The first one is <a class="reference" href="http://www.familysearch.org/eng/default.asp">Family search</a>  where they provide a tool to search for family history and genealogy. Also they are working to define a standard format to exchange citation with <a class="reference" href="http://openlibrary.org/.">Open Library</a>.
<a class="reference" href="http://www.democracylab.org/">Democracy Lab</a> provide an application to collect votes and build geographic statitics based on political interests. They will at some point publish data semantically so that their application data could be consumed.</p>
<p>It also was for us the occasion of introducing CubicWeb to the BayPIGgies folks. The same <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.fr/publications/europython2009-cubicweb">presentation</a> as the one held at Europython 2009.
I'd like to take the opportunity to answer a question I did not manage to answer at that time. The question was: how different is CubicWeb from Freebase Parallax in terms of interface and views filters? Before answering this question let's detail what Freebase Parallax is.</p>
<p>Freebase <a class="reference" href="http://mqlx.com/~david/parallax">Parallax</a> provides a new way to browse and explore data in Freebase.
It allows to browse data from a set of data to a related set of data. This interface enables to aggregate visualization. For instance, given the set of US presidents, different types of views could be applied, such as a timeline view, where the user could set up which start and end date to use to draw the timeline. So generic views (which applies to any data) are customizable by the user.</p>
<img align="left" alt="http://res.freebase.com/s/f64a2f0cc4534b2b17140fd169cee825a7ed7ddcefe0bf81570301c72a83c0a8/resources/images/freebase-logo.png" class="align-left" src="http://res.freebase.com/s/f64a2f0cc4534b2b17140fd169cee825a7ed7ddcefe0bf81570301c72a83c0a8/resources/images/freebase-logo.png" />
<p>The search powered by Parallax is very similar to CubicWeb faceted search, except that Parallax provides the user with a list of suggested filters to add in addition to the default one, the user can even remove a filter. That is something we could think about for CubicWeb: provide a generated faceted search so that the user could decide which filters to choose.</p>
<p>Parallax also provides related topics to the current data set which ease navigation between sets of data.
The main difference I could see with the view filter offered by Parallax and CubicWeb is that Parallax provides the same views to any type of data whereas CubicWeb has specific views depending on the data type and generic views that applies to any type of data.
This is a nice Web interface to browse data and it could be a good source of inspiration for CubicWeb.</p>
<div align="center" class="align-center"><img alt="http://www.zgeek.com/forum/gallery/files/6/3/2/img_228_96x96.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://www.zgeek.com/forum/gallery/files/6/3/2/img_228_96x96.jpg" /></div>
<p>During this talk, I mentionned that CubicWeb now understands <a class="reference" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/">SPARQL</a> queries thanks to the <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/project/fyzz/">fyzz</a> parser.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/zi7_LkueHLA/344573">[cubicweb] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/GA-4QEbeUf0/9630">[logilab] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/o56b5TqtoRs/344425">[cubicweb] Graphing version progress</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/pavEfIaZcmY/9209">[logilab] Nous allons à PyConFr 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/nct5PaugpYM/9152">[logilab] Almost reached 1000 tickets</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/3yWbpUOUNKc/9097">[logilab] iclassmethod decorator to define both a class and an instance method in one go</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/TTSEwjKo2L0/8815">[logilab] Venez nous rendre visite à Solution Linux 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/FMMhRpY4xNs/344349">[cubicweb] News from Europython 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/viYkOez-KvY/9579">[logilab] EuroPython 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/RItpr_z3C_A/344822">[cubicweb] Sparkles everywhere, CubicWeb gets fizzy</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/yAy0KLWb-Vc/9827]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-28 17:58:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] Python African Tour :  De retour de l'étape du Sénégal]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Après le Maroc en décembre 2008, nous venons de vivre l'étape sénégalaise du Tour. Voici un petit résumé des activités.]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://zope.afpy.org/Members/kamon/pat-senegal-report]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-27 15:17:18</pubDate>
    <category>A la une</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[tarek] Words on : Distribute, Distutils, PEP 376, PEP 386, PEP 345]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[I am taking a break for a week starting tomorrow morning. My wife made it clear : my laptop and internet are totally forbidden during 7 days. So I thaught it was a good opportunity to make a status of all the projects that are going on in the packaging world.
Distribute
The setuptools fork is doing [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=tarekziade.wordpress.com&blog=448161&post=875&subd=tarekziade&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/24/words-on-distribute-distutils-pep-376-pep-386-pep-345/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-24 22:56:05</pubDate>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[tarek] Vacations + a new job]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[I am officialy on vacations !
I&#8217;ve just finished my time at Alterway / Ingeniweb, where I was CTO for the last two years. Well CTO was a translation for &#8220;Directeur technique&#8221; in French, which is more like &#8220;head of developments&#8221;. So I was like some kind of lead developer, but without a code project  [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=tarekziade.wordpress.com&blog=448161&post=868&subd=tarekziade&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/24/vacations-a-new-job/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-24 16:38:33</pubDate>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[tarek] Preparing to release Distribute 0.6]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[According to the poll, The name of the fork will be Distribute !
The code should not be changed anymore at this point, and I am working on the bootstraping so installing Distribute will work with an existing Setuptools installation and will replace it for the applications that requires it.
This is done by detecting an installation [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=tarekziade.wordpress.com&blog=448161&post=863&subd=tarekziade&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/22/preparing-to-release-distribute-0-6/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-22 17:30:24</pubDate>
    <category>distutils</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[ccomb] Professional Magento deployment with Fabric and Mercurial]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="document">
<blockquote class="highlights">
<div class="line-block">
<div class="line">Author : Christophe Combelles for <a href="http://emencia.com" class="reference external">Emencia</a></div>
</div>
</blockquote>
<a href="http://emencia.fr" class="reference external image-reference"><img src="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/static/logo_emencia.png" alt="logo Emencia" class="align-right" align="right" /></a>
<div id="contents" class="contents topic">
<p class="topic-title first">Contents</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#warning" id="id6" class="reference internal">Warning</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#quickstart" id="id7" class="reference internal">Quickstart</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#introductions-and-prerequisites" id="id8" class="reference internal">Introductions and prerequisites</a><ul>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#magento" id="id9" class="reference internal">Magento</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#fabric" id="id10" class="reference internal">Fabric</a><ul>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#installation" id="id11" class="reference internal">Installation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#documentation" id="id12" class="reference internal">Documentation</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#mercurial" id="id13" class="reference internal">Mercurial</a><ul>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id1" id="id14" class="reference internal">Installation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#mq-extension" id="id15" class="reference internal">MQ Extension</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#the-fabfile" id="id16" class="reference internal">The Fabfile</a><ul>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#configuration" id="id17" class="reference internal">Configuration</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#check-the-server-environment" id="id18" class="reference internal">Check the server environment</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#preparing-the-server-for-deployment" id="id19" class="reference internal">Preparing the server for deployment</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#deploy-magento" id="id20" class="reference internal">Deploy Magento</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#check-magento-version" id="id21" class="reference internal">Check Magento version</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#customize-magento" id="id22" class="reference internal">Customize Magento</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#upgrade-magento" id="id23" class="reference internal">Upgrade Magento</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#retrieve-the-deployment-history" id="id24" class="reference internal">Retrieve the deployment history</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="warning" class="section">
<h3><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id6" class="toc-backref">Warning</a></h3>
<p>This article and the provided fabfile are just a food for thought and need to be discussed!
It currently does not support database creation. Feedback appreciated. An alternative solution using <a href="http://www.buildout.org" class="reference external">Buildout</a> is provided by Alex Clark <a href="http://aclark.net/Members/aclark/blog/a-lamp-buildout-for-wordpress-and-other-php-apps" class="reference external">here</a>.</p>
</div>
<div id="quickstart" class="section">
<h3><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id7" class="toc-backref">Quickstart</a></h3>
<p>If you are in a hurry, if you already know Magento, Mercurial, MQ Extension and Fabric and
you don't like to read documentation, here is a quickstart for Debian or Ubuntu.</p>
<p>Install the required tools on your machine:</p>
<pre class="literal-block">$ sudo aptitude install python2.5 python-setuptools
$ sudo easy_install fabric==0.1.1
$ wget https://cody.gorfou.fr/hg/magento_fabfile/raw-file/tip/fabfile.py
</pre>
<p>Prepare a Debian server for deployment:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> prepare_debian</blockquote>
<p>Deploy Magento 1.2.1:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> deploy:1.2.1</blockquote>
<p>Upgrade Magento to 1.3.1:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> upgrade:1.3.1</blockquote>
<p>Check installed version:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> get_version</blockquote>
<p>Professional means safe and quick. The core idea is to deploy <a href="http://www.magentocommerce.com" class="reference external">Magento</a> on the
server into a <a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com" class="reference external">Mercurial</a> repository, so that everything is versioned, and
to use <a href="http://www.nongnu.org/fab/" class="reference external">Fabric</a> to automate the deployment, the upgrade, and the patches
management.  The main Mercurial history is used for upgrades, and <a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/MqExtension" class="reference external">MQ</a> patches are
used for extensions and customization.  During an upgrade, all patches are
unapplied, diffs are applied, then patches are reapplied. Mercurial is used to
simulate a transactional system, so if an upgrade fails, everything is safely
reverted to the previous state.</p>
<p>Everything is done using a single fabfile. The fabfile defines useful commands
for deployment or upgrades. The actual Mercurial commands are defined in the
fabfile. As a result, deployments and upgrades should be feasible without any
Python, Fabric or Mercurial knowledge.</p>
<p>Note that such a deployment leads to the exact same result as a manual
deployment. The only difference will be a <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">.hg</span></tt> directory containing the
Mercurial repository. This directory is located one level higher than the
Magento installation, so it is not exposed to the web (provided your Apache
virtualhost points to the Magento directory).</p>
</div>
<div id="introductions-and-prerequisites" class="section">
<h3><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id8" class="toc-backref">Introductions and prerequisites</a></h3>
<div id="magento" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id9" class="toc-backref">Magento</a></h4>
<p>Magento is an eCommerce platform written in PHP. It allows you to create online
shops quickly and easily, with unprecedented flexibility and excellent usability.
Like almost any other PHP application, it can be installed very
easily, with two different methods:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul class="simple">
<li>download the full Magento archive, extract it on your hard disk, then upload all the files
onto your server by FTP. Or,</li>
<li>download a small downloader package, extract it on your hard disk, upload all
the files onto your server by FTP, then access the downloader through your
browser and let it finish downloading and installing the remaining files.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>That's the common way of installing Magento on a shared hosting. If you own a
dedicated or private server, the method is exactly the same, except that you do
everything directly from the shell on your server.</p>
<p>Easy? Yes, if you install a single Magento instance. As soon as you are a web
agency or integrator, and if you deploy, customize, upgrade and maintain a bunch
of Magento instances, you will loose a lot of time, and possibly do errors. You
probably won't be able to safely upgrade a heavily customized (or even manually
patched) installation of Magento.  Worst of all, you won't be able to <em>know</em>
what has been done on a particular instance, unless you (and all your staff) are
very well organized. But you are, aren't you? ;-)</p>
<p>If you do professional Magento deployment, you definitely want to:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul class="simple">
<li>Quickly deploy without manually downloading, uploading, chmod'ing, etc.</li>
<li>Immediately put the installation under version control, to keep a full history
of all the upgrades and customizations</li>
<li>Be able to remotely upgrade Magento with diff files provided by <a href="http://www.varien.com" class="reference external">Varien</a> (the company
that distributes and maintains the Magento source code)</li>
<li>Be able to apply diffs, <strong>even</strong> if you heavily modified the Magento source code, or
if you have a lot of installed extensions.</li>
<li>Instantly (and remotely) know which version is installed</li>
<li>Be able to deploy again a custom Magento installation, with custom skins,
custom extensions, custom patches, etc.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>To be able to achieve all these tasks, we will use three very good tools:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul class="simple">
<li><a href="http://www.nongnu.org/fab/" class="reference external">Fabric</a></li>
<li><a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com" class="reference external">Mercurial</a></li>
<li>Mercurial <a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/MqExtension" class="reference external">MQ Extension</a></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div id="fabric" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id10" class="toc-backref">Fabric</a></h4>
<p>Fabric is a simple tool that allows you to run remote commands on several
servers, upload files on these servers, and automate things by creating simple
commands.</p>
<p>For instance, we will be able to deploy Magento 1.3.0 with a single command line like
this:</p>
<p>$ fab deploy:1.3.0</p>
<div id="installation" class="section">
<h5><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id11" class="toc-backref">Installation</a></h5>
<p>Fabric is needed on your machine, not on the server.</p>
<p>To install Fabric, you first need to install Python, since Fabric is written in
Python. If you use a Debian or Ubuntu system, just run the following commands as
root (or prepend <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">sudo</span></tt> if you're not root but sudoer):</p>
<pre class="literal-block"># aptitude install python2.5 python-setuptools
# easy_install fabric==0.1.1
</pre>
<p>If you're using MacOs or Windows, the steps are similar: first, check you have
Python 2.5, then easy_install fabric. Note that I have no idea whether Fabric
works on Windows or not.</p>
<p>You should now have a``fa`` shell command available. If you run it without arguments, you will
discover which commands are available. If your current shell directory contains a
<tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">fabfile.py</span></tt> file, additional commands are available.</p>
</div>
<div id="documentation" class="section">
<h5><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id12" class="toc-backref">Documentation</a></h5>
<blockquote>
<ul class="simple">
<li>Currently here: <a href="http://www.nongnu.org/fab/documentation.html" class="reference external">http://www.nongnu.org/fab/documentation.html</a></li>
<li>Soon here: <a href="http://fabfile.org" class="reference external">http://fabfile.org</a></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
<div id="mercurial" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id13" class="toc-backref">Mercurial</a></h4>
<p><a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com" class="reference external">Mercurial</a> is a very fast, easy-to-use and well-known Distributed Version Control
System, used by large projects such as Mozilla, OpenJDK, OpenSolaris or Python.
If you already use Subversion, you will be able to use Mercurial in a matter of
minutes. The main conceptual difference is that every <em>checkout</em> is also a full
repository. So it is called a <em>clone</em> instead of a <em>checkout</em>, and you do
check-ins locally. Mercurial is much more powerful than Subversion for branching
and merging, and comes with a lot of interesting plugins. It also avoids
maintaining a central repository. When you want to version-control a new project
or directory, just run <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">hg</span> <span class="pre">init</span></tt> and that's all.  Then you can start adding
files in the repository and commit changes offline.  You will be able to
synchronize your repository with another one, locally or remotely.</p>
<div id="id1" class="section">
<h5><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id14" class="toc-backref">Installation</a></h5>
<p>Mercurial is needed on the server, not on your machine.</p>
<p>Recent Linux systems already offer a Mercurial package. On Debian or Ubuntu, just
run the following command as root (or sudo) on your server:</p>
<blockquote>
# aptitude install mercurial</blockquote>
<p>If you want a more recent version or if Mercurial is not already packaged,
install it with easy_install:</p>
<blockquote>
# easy_install mercurial</blockquote>
</div>
<div id="mq-extension" class="section">
<h5><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id15" class="toc-backref">MQ Extension</a></h5>
<p>Now you should enable the <a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/MqExtension" class="reference external">MQ Extension</a>. This extension offers patch management,
just like <em>quilt</em> does, but integrated with Mercurial. It will be used for
Magento extensions and customizations.</p>
<p>To enable the MQ Mercurial extension on the server, add the following line in the
[extensions] section of your .hgrc.:</p>
<blockquote>
hgext.mq =</blockquote>
<p>You can check whether MQ is enabled by running: <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">hg</span> <span class="pre">help</span> <span class="pre">qinit</span></tt></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="the-fabfile" class="section">
<h3><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id16" class="toc-backref">The Fabfile</a></h3>
<p>After installing <em>Fabric</em> on your machine and <em>Mercurial/MQ</em> on the server, all you
need to do is download the <em>fabfile</em>. You can get the latest version here:</p>
<p><a href="https://cody.gorfou.fr/hg/magento_fabfile/raw-file/tip/fabfile.py" class="reference external">https://cody.gorfou.fr/hg/magento_fabfile/raw-file/tip/fabfile.py</a></p>
<p>When you run the <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">fab</span></tt> shell command, Fabric will look for a <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">fabfile.py</span></tt> in
the current directory. All the fabric commands defined in the fabfile will be
instantly available to Fabric. After downloading the <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">fabfile.py</span></tt>, go to the
directory containing this file, and run: <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">fab</span></tt>. You should see some specific
commands, such as <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">deploy</span></tt>, <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">upgrade</span></tt> or <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">get_version</span></tt>.</p>
<div id="configuration" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id17" class="toc-backref">Configuration</a></h4>
<p>You need to adapt some parameters to your environment. Open the fabfile
and look at the first few variables defined at the top of the file:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul class="simple">
<li><tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">config.wwwdir</span></tt> is the target directory in the server. You should replace
'/var/www/site' with the intended DocumentRoot of your Magento site.</li>
<li><tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">config.wwwuser</span></tt> is the system user that will own all the files in the
Magento installation. The typical value for a Debian system is 'www-data'.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div id="check-the-server-environment" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id18" class="toc-backref">Check the server environment</a></h4>
<p>Make sure your server can be accessed through SSH.
To check if the server is ready for a Magento deployment, run:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab check</blockquote>
<p>Anyway, this command will automatically be run before any other command. It
checks whether required tools are available, such as <em>wget</em>, <em>python</em>, <em>mercurial</em>, etc.</p>
</div>
<div id="preparing-the-server-for-deployment" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id19" class="toc-backref">Preparing the server for deployment</a></h4>
<p>In order to be able to run Magento, your server should offer several required
tools, such as PHP5 or MySQL, and tools used for deployments and upgrades, such
as <em>Mercurial</em>, <em>wget</em> or <em>patch</em>.</p>
<p>If you want to prepare a Debian/Ubuntu server for deployment, run:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> prepare_debian</blockquote>
<p>If you want to see what it does, just look at the corresponding command in the
fabfile.</p>
</div>
<div id="deploy-magento" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id20" class="toc-backref">Deploy Magento</a></h4>
<p>Now that your server is ready for deployment, you can deploy Magento 1.2.1 with:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> deploy:1.2.1</blockquote>
<p><tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">set_host:user@host</span></tt> is a required command if you did not set the fab_host
config variable at the beginning of the fabfile. Use it to set the user and host
for deployment. Note that the user should be sudoer on the server.</p>
<p>If you deploy twice, the previous site is not overwritten, but renamed with a
timestamp.</p>
</div>
<div id="check-magento-version" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id21" class="toc-backref">Check Magento version</a></h4>
<p>To retrieve the version number of the deployed Magento instance, run:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> get_version</blockquote>
</div>
<div id="customize-magento" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id22" class="toc-backref">Customize Magento</a></h4>
<p>After installing a Magento extension, you can create a savepoint to your
repository. The savepoint is created as an MQ patch, so it can be unapplied at a
later time. Unapplying is useful when you want to upgrade Magento with the diff
files provided by Varien.</p>
<p>To create a savepoint, run:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> savepoint</blockquote>
<p>This command will fail is there is no added, removed or modified files in the
repository.</p>
<p>TODO: this is unclear when we should commit changes as a changeset, or create an
MQ patch. MQ Patches are probably useful</p>
</div>
<div id="upgrade-magento" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id23" class="toc-backref">Upgrade Magento</a></h4>
<p>When you want to upgrade Magento, just run the following command with the target
version:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> upgrade:1.3.1</blockquote>
<p>It will compare the current installed version, and will successively upgrade to
the wanted version, using each diff file. The location of the diff files is
known by the fabfile, so this procedure doesn't require any additional
information. If you have created savepoints, they will be unapplied so that the
upgrade of Magento won't fail due to unpatchable modifications.</p>
<p>TODO: the diff files may provide patches to some extensions not installed by
default (ex: blue or modern skin). In this case, the extension won't be
patched. This is a problem. The MQ patch should probably be used for alpha or
beta extensions, not for the stable or official ones?</p>
</div>
<div id="retrieve-the-deployment-history" class="section">
<h4><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/tags/python/feed.atom#id24" class="toc-backref">Retrieve the deployment history</a></h4>
<p>Run:</p>
<blockquote>
$ fab set_host:<a href="mailto:user@host" class="reference external">user@host</a> get_glog</blockquote>
<p>This is the same as running <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">hg</span> <span class="pre">glog</span></tt> on the server.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/2007/12/13/tutoriel-sur-buildout">[ccomb] Tutoriel sur Buildout</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/2009/2/17/sortie-de-zope-3-4">[ccomb] Sortie de Zope 3.4</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/2009/7/19/zinebuildout-a-buildout-for-zine">[ccomb] zinebuildout 0.5 : a buildout for Zine</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://fantomas.willbreak.it/blog/2009/may/01/paye-ta-fabric/">[fantomas] Paye ta Fabric !</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/post/2008/12/16/D%C3%A9ployer-vos-applications-avec-fabric">[nsteinmetz] Déployer vos applications avec fabric</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/2009/7/20/professional-magento-deployment-with-fabric-and-mercurial]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-20 23:37:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[ccomb] zinebuildout 0.5 : a buildout for Zine]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="document">
<img src="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/static/zinelogo.png" alt="Zine logo" class="align-left" align="left" />
<p>This blog is powered by <a href="http://zine.pocoo.org" class="reference external">Zine</a>, a blog engine written in Python (with Werkzeug, Jinja2 and SQLAlchemy) and I'm very satisfied with it. I first want to thank its main author, Armin Ronacher (mitsuhiko) and the contributors. It's development is not as fast as I initially expected, but <a href="http://dev.pocoo.org/hg/zine-main" class="reference external">it's mercurial repository</a> shows a constant activity:</p>
<div align="center" class="align-center"><img src="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/static/zine-activity.png" alt="Zine activity" class="align-center" /></div>
<p>Yes I know, I should contribute... Until now, I did not find any time to do it, but this could change in a near future.</p>
<p>When I first installed it, I was surprised there is no distutils/setuptools setup.py file, just a classic 'configure &amp;&amp; make' procedure. The authors probably want to avoid any Python-specific tasks during installation, so that it is more widely adopted. They also probably don't like setuptools (BTW, setuptools is being <a href="http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/19/the-strange-world-of-packaging-forking-setuptools/" class="reference external">forked</a> for real by Tarek). The same applies to the deployment: Zine is expected to be deployed with <a href="http://code.google.com/p/modwsgi/" class="reference external">mod_wsgi</a>, which promises to offer easy and shared Python hosting to the masses.</p>
<p>But I'm used to Python tools, I don't find that typing "sudo python setup.py install" or something similar is difficult, I like to deploy with PasteDeploy, and I like to work with <a href="http://www.buildout.org" class="reference external">Buildout</a>. That's why I've packaged Zine in a setuptools-enabled buildout.</p>
<p>Below is the content of the README file for version 0.5 of the buildout. I've also added a Twitter widget, but this one should better go in Zine itself, or in an external plugin. You can see the result right here, on the right.</p>
<p><a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/zinebuildout/" class="reference external">http://pypi.python.org/pypi/zinebuildout/</a></p>
<div id="installation" class="section">
<h3>Installation</h3>
<p>This package allows you to install Zine and its dependencies in a sandbox with
buildout, then serve it with any WSGI server while using the Paste facilities
for WSGI stack configuration.</p>
<div id="install-zine" class="section">
<h4>Install Zine:</h4>
<p>Download and extract the zinebuildout archive from PyPI,
(or clone it with: hg clone <a href="https://cody.gorfou.fr/hg/zinebuildout" class="reference external">https://cody.gorfou.fr/hg/zinebuildout</a> ).
You don't need to easy_install it.
Then run:</p>
<pre class="literal-block">$ python bootstrap.py
$ ./bin/buildout
</pre>
</div>
<div id="configure-zine" class="section">
<h4>Configure Zine:</h4>
<p>Edit "deploy.ini" to adapt <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">instance_folder</span></tt>, <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">host</span></tt> and <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">port</span></tt> to
your needs. You don't need to change anything if you just want to try it on
your local host.</p>
</div>
<div id="start-zine" class="section">
<h4>Start Zine:</h4>
<p>In foreground:</p>
<pre class="literal-block">$ ./bin/paster serve deploy.ini
</pre>
<p>Or in background:</p>
<pre class="literal-block">$ ./bin/paster serve --daemon deploy.ini
</pre>
</div>
<div id="optional-twitter-widget" class="section">
<h4>Optional Twitter widget</h4>
<p>This distribution offers a Twitter widget that displays the N latests tweets of
your timeline. To use it, just add the following line in the '_widgets.html'
file of your Zine theme:</p>
<blockquote>
{{ widgets.tweets('ccomb', 5) }}</blockquote>
<p>Replace 'ccomb' with your twitter account, and 5 with the number of tweets you
want to display.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/2009/7/20/professional-magento-deployment-with-fabric-and-mercurial">[ccomb] Professional Magento deployment with Fabric and Mercurial</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/2009/7/19/zinebuildout-a-buildout-for-zine]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-19 21:26:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[fantomas] Le temps des releases : Django-smileys]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Parfois il est temps de se sortir les doigts du code, et d'en parler !<br />Mais pour en parler, il faut documenter, ce qui prend un peu de temps, mais j'y travaille.</p><p>Pour commencer je vais vous présenter une de mes applications favorites, par sa simplicité et son utilité incroyable. <img class="smiley" src="http://fantomas.willbreak.it//img/smileys/mrgreen.gif" /></p><p><strong>Django-smileys</strong> est une application <strong>Django</strong> comme son nom l'indique, permettant d'inclure facilement dans ses templates des smileys, de ce genre <img class="smiley" src="http://fantomas.willbreak.it//img/smileys/smile.gif" /> <img class="smiley" src="http://fantomas.willbreak.it//img/smileys/razz.gif" />.</p><p>Pour cela, une fois l'application téléchargée et installée dans votre projet django, il vous suffit dans vos templates d'utiliser le filtre qui va convertir tout les code smileys définis dans SMILEYS_LIST.</p><pre>{% load smiley_tags %}<br /><br />{{ object.content|smileys }}</pre><p>Plutôt facile non ? Surtout que l'on peut maintenant convertir tout type de contenu texte.</p><p>La liste des smileys est configurable, ainsi que l'url de dépot et la classe d'habillage CSS.</p><p>Pour télécharger ce projet hallucinant : <a title="Dépot de Django-smileys" href="http://github.com/Fantomas42/django-smileys/tree/master">http://github.com/Fantomas42/django-smileys/tree/master</a></p><p>Bientôt d'autres releases.</p>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://fantomas.willbreak.it/blog/2009/jul/19/release-django-smileys/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-19 11:25:48</pubDate>
    <category>Développement</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[tarek] The strange world of packaging – forking setuptools]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Again, like a year ago, people had enough of the fact that the setuptools project is not maintained since 9 months.
Phillip Eby explained that he doesn&#8217;t have time to do it unless someone would pay him for that. But in the meantime, he doesn&#8217;t bless anyone to do it. Well, he has blessed some people [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=tarekziade.wordpress.com&blog=448161&post=856&subd=tarekziade&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/19/the-strange-world-of-packaging-forking-setuptools/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-19 09:59:08</pubDate>
    <category>packaging</category>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[carlchenet] Fin du concours de contribution à Debian]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[J&#8217;ai appris à mon retour de Berlin après quelques jours de vacances passés là-bas que, comme annoncé sur le blog de Raphaël Hertzog, je fais parti des heureux gagnants du concours de contribution à Debian ! Je remporte donc un abonnement d&#8217;un an au GNU/Linux Magazine France des éditions Diamonds et le Cahier de l&#8217;admin [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=carlchenet.wordpress.com&blog=7722010&post=73&subd=carlchenet&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://carlchenet.wordpress.com/2009/07/15/fin-du-concours-de-contribution-a-debian/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-15 17:29:11</pubDate>
    <category>debian-fr</category>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] IPMI plugin for Munin python code published]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9368?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9368?vid=download" />
<p>As you might have noticed we quite like <a class="reference" href="http://munin.projects.linpro.no/">munin</a>. We use it quite a bit to monitor how our servers and services are doing. One of the things we like about munin is obviously that the plugins can be written in <a class="reference" href="http://www.python.org">python</a> (and perl, bash  and ruby).</p>
<p>On a few recent servers we started playing with <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intelligent_Platform_Management_Interface">IPMI</a> to sensor the temperature, watts, fan's rpms etc. So we went out looking for a munin plugin for that. We found Peter Palfrader's ruby plugins. There was one small glitch though, we came across a simple bug : the &quot;ipmitool -I open sensor&quot; can be real long to execute on certain machines, so configuring the plugin was a bit painful and running it too. Changing the ruby code was a bit tricky since we don't really know ruby... so we did a quick rewrite of the plugin in python... with a few optimizations.</p>
<p>It's not really complete but works for us, and might be useful to you, so we're publishing the hg repo. You can get the <a class="reference" href="http://hg.logilab.org/munin_ipmi_plugins/archive/f2e7c91f5ea7.tar.gz">tgz</a> or browse the <a class="reference" href="http://hg.logilab.org/munin_ipmi_plugins/file/f2e7c91f5ea7">source</a>.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/xIx3wVIeerc/9297">[logilab] hgview 1.0.0 released!</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://gillesfabio.com/blog/2009/01/29/creer-un-blog-avec-django/">[gfabio] Créer un blog avec Django</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://www.gawel.org/weblog/fr/2008/06/la-vie-apres-pycon">[gawel] Il y a de la vie après PyCON !!!</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://www.gawel.org/weblog/fr/2007/04/journees-python-francophones">[gawel] Journées Python Francophones</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/9dxfHA5A8ko/9371]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-15 09:42:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] AFPyro le 16 Juillet à l'Apostrophe café]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://zope.afpy.org/Members/michael/afpyrojuillet09]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-15 09:13:11</pubDate>
    <category>A la une</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] News from Europython 2009]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.europython.eu/images/europython_logo.png" class="align-right" src="http://www.europython.eu/images/europython_logo.png" />
<p>Nicolas gave a talk at <a class="reference" href="http://www.europython.eu/">Europython2009</a> about CubicWeb. Reinout Van Rees posted his <a class="reference" href="http://reinout.vanrees.org/weblog/2009/07/01/ep-cubicweb.html">notes</a> about the talk on his <a class="reference" href="http://reinout.vanrees.org/">blog</a>. Thanks Reinout. You may also read Nicolas' <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.fr/publications/europython2009-cubicweb">slides</a> and watch his lightning <a class="reference" href="http://europython09.blip.tv/file/2338586">talk</a>.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/viYkOez-KvY/9579">[logilab] EuroPython 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/yAy0KLWb-Vc/9827">[logilab] Logilab at OSCON 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/FMMhRpY4xNs/344349]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-14 22:54:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9631?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9631?vid=download" />
<p>I am pleased to announce that <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org">CubicWeb</a> will be presented during a BayPIGgies meeting that will exceptionally take place in the <a class="reference" href="http://en.oreilly.com/oscon2009/public/schedule/detail/10349">OSCON</a> conference building as the closing event of the Bird of Feathers on July 23rd at 8pm.</p>
<p>Joins us to get to know more about <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org">CubicWeb</a>.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/zi7_LkueHLA/344573">[cubicweb] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/yAy0KLWb-Vc/9827">[logilab] Logilab at OSCON 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/o56b5TqtoRs/344425">[cubicweb] Graphing version progress</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/pavEfIaZcmY/9209">[logilab] Nous allons à PyConFr 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/nct5PaugpYM/9152">[logilab] Almost reached 1000 tickets</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/3yWbpUOUNKc/9097">[logilab] iclassmethod decorator to define both a class and an instance method in one go</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/TTSEwjKo2L0/8815">[logilab] Venez nous rendre visite à Solution Linux 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/GA-4QEbeUf0/9630]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-14 21:57:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] Revue de presse python semaine 29]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Revue de presse sur le langage python sans aucune prétention.]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://www.afpy.org/Members/boussard/revue_presse_python_29]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-13 01:44:52</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] Revue de presse python semaine 29]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Revue de presse sur le langage python sans aucune prétention.]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://zope.afpy.org/Members/boussard/revue_presse_python_29]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-13 01:44:52</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] Graphing version progress]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>As you might have noticed we've upgraded <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org">http://www.logilab.org</a> and <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org">http://www.cubicweb.org</a> to CubicWeb 3.3 and a bunch of cubes were upgraded too. We can now benefit from a few cool bugfixes and features on those two forges.</p>
<p>One of them I like and wish to mention is the graphing of a project's progress as a <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burn_down_chart">Burn Down Chart</a>, you can see an example below. We're using the some <a class="reference" href="http://jquery.com/">jQuery</a> magic here, and so you can roll over the mouse to get more info on the graph... (not on the screenshot below). This type of graph is generated on all the version views... This is particularly useful on some of our extranets to see the progress of a version (and if tickets were added along the way).</p>
<div align="center" class="align-center"><img alt="http://www.cubicweb.org/image/344424?vid=download" class="align-center" src="http://www.cubicweb.org/image/344424?vid=download" /></div>
<p>For the coders out there you can check out <em>cubicweb/web/views/plots.py</em> and the example in the forge cube.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://www.gawel.org/weblog/en/2008/12/skinning-with-pyquery-and-deliverance">[gawel] Skinning with pyquery and deliverance</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/zi7_LkueHLA/344573">[cubicweb] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/yAy0KLWb-Vc/9827">[logilab] Logilab at OSCON 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/GA-4QEbeUf0/9630">[logilab] CubicWeb at BayPiggies/OSCON in July</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/pavEfIaZcmY/9209">[logilab] Nous allons à PyConFr 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/nct5PaugpYM/9152">[logilab] Almost reached 1000 tickets</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/3yWbpUOUNKc/9097">[logilab] iclassmethod decorator to define both a class and an instance method in one go</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/TTSEwjKo2L0/8815">[logilab] Venez nous rendre visite à Solution Linux 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/o56b5TqtoRs/344425]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-13 01:28:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] Cubicweb to be presented at French Linux Conference]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="left" alt="http://www.solutionslinux.fr/images/index_07.jpg" class="align-left" src="http://www.solutionslinux.fr/images/index_07.jpg" />
<p>The CubicWeb plateform will be on display at the French conference about linux &quot;<a class="reference" href="http://www.solutionslinux.fr/">Solution Linux</a>&quot; hosted in Paris in the next 3 days. You can meet us at the <a class="reference" href="http://www.systematic-paris-region.org/">System&#64;tic</a> stand or see us talk about it during a talk about Web2 this afternoon.</p>
<p>More info in french on the <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/blogentry/8815">Logilab.org Blog</a>.</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/TTSEwjKo2L0/8815">[logilab] Venez nous rendre visite à Solution Linux 2009</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/YSOf9cb18fw/320283]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-13 01:27:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] INSEE, XML and RDF]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://insee.fr/fr/css/images/logo_insee.gif" class="align-right" src="http://insee.fr/fr/css/images/logo_insee.gif" />
<p>I discovered that the French Institute for Statistics and Economic Studies (INSEE) has published part of its data as XML and RDF:</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li><a class="reference" href="http://xml.insee.fr/">http://xml.insee.fr/</a></li>
<li><a class="reference" href="http://rdf.insee.fr/geo/">http://rdf.insee.fr/geo/</a></li>
</ul>
<p>We will try to put that data to good use.</p>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/c9YJqRB2ni0/344467]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-13 01:26:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] AFPyro le 16 Juillet à l'Apostrophe café]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://www.afpy.org/Members/michael/afpyrojuillet09]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-12 13:54:34</pubDate>
    <category>A la une</category>
    <category>A la une</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] Quizz WolframAlpha]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9609?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9609?vid=download" />
<p>Wolfram Alpha is a web front-end to huge database of information covering very different topics ranging from mathematical functions to genetics, geography, astronomy, etc.</p>
<p>When you search for a word, it will try to match it with one of the objects it as in its database and display all the information it has concerning that object. For example it can tell you a lot about the <a class="reference" href="http://www94.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=halley+comet">Halley Comet</a>, including where it is at the moment you ask the query. This is the main difference with, say Wikipedia, that will know a lot about that <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halley_comet">comet</a> in general, but is not meant to compute its location in the sky at the moment you enter your query.</p>
<p>Searches are not limited to words. One can key in commands like <a class="reference" href="http://www34.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=weather+in+paris+in+june+2009">weather in Paris in june 2009</a> or <a class="reference" href="http://www34.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=x^2+sin(x)">x^2+sin(x)</a> and get results for those precise queries. The processing of the input query is far from bad, since it returns results to questions like <a class="reference" href="http://www34.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=what+are+the+cities+of+france+">what are the cities of France</a>, but I would not call it state of the art natural language processing since that query returns the largest cities instead of just the cities it knows about and the question <a class="reference" href="http://www34.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=what+are+the+smallest+cities+of+france+">what are the smallest cities of France</a> will not return any result. Natural language processing is a very difficult problem, though, especially when done in the open world as it is the case there with a engine available to the wide public on the internet.</p>
<p>For <a class="reference" href="http://www34.wolframalpha.com/examples/">more examples</a>, visit the WolframAlpha website, where you will also be able to <a class="reference" href="http://community.wolframalpha.com/">post feature requests</a> or, if you are a developer, get documentation about the <a class="reference" href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/developers.html">WolframAlpha API</a> and maybe use it as a web service in your application when you need to answer certain types of questions.</p>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/KD4qFeSluAg/9608]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-10 17:05:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] EuroPython 2009]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9580?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9580?vid=download" />
<p>Once again Logilab sponsored the <a class="reference" href="http://www.europython.eu/">EuroPython</a> conference. We would like to thank
the organization team (especially John Pinner and Laura Creighton) for their
hard work. The Conservatoire is a very central location in Birmingham and
walking around the city center and along the canals was nice. The website was
helpful when preparing the trip and made it easy to find places where to eat and
stay. The conference program was full of talks about interesting topics.</p>
<p>I presented <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/">CubicWeb</a> and spent a large part of my talk explaining what is the
semantic web and what features we need in the tools we will use to be part of
that web of data. I insisted on the fact that CubicWeb is made of <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/doc/en/intro/concepts/">two parts</a>,
the web engine and the data repository, and that the repository can be used
without the web engine. I demonstrated this with a TurboGears application that
used the CubicWeb repository as its persistence layer. RQL in TurboGears! See <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.fr/publications/europython2009-cubicweb">my
slides</a> and Reinout Van Rees' <a class="reference" href="http://reinout.vanrees.org/weblog/2009/07/01/ep-cubicweb.html">write-up</a>.</p>
<p>Christian Tismer took over the development of <a class="reference" href="http://psyco.sourceforge.net/">Psyco</a> a few months ago. He said he
recently removed some bugs that were show stoppers, including one that was
generating way too many recompilations. His new version looks very
promising. Performance improved, long numbers are supported, 64bit support may
become possible, generators work... and Stackless is about to be rebuilt on top of
Psyco! Psyco 2.0 should be out today.</p>
<p>I had a nice chat with Cosmin Basca about the Semantic Web. He suggested using
Mako as a templating language for CubicWeb. Cosmin is doing his PhD at DERI and
develops <a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/surfrdf/wiki/dbpediaLiveExample">SurfRDF</a> which is an Object-RDF mapper that wraps a SPARQL endpoint to
provide &quot;discoverable&quot; objects. See his <a class="reference" href="http://wiki.europython.eu/TalkMaterials?action=AttachFile&amp;do=get&amp;target=SuRF+%E2%80%93+Tapping+into+the+Web+of+Data+EUROPYTHON09.pdf">slides</a> and Reinout Van Rees' <a class="reference" href="http://reinout.vanrees.org/weblog/2009/07/01/ep-web-of-data.html">summary</a>
of his talk.</p>
<p>I saw a lightning talk about the <a class="reference" href="http://www.nagare.org/">Nagare</a> framework which refuses to use
templating languages, for the same reason we do not use them in CubicWeb. Is
their <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">h.something</span></tt> the right way of doing things? The <a class="reference" href="http://www.nagare.org/trac/blog/html-structuration-inheritance-aggregation">example</a> reminds me of the
C++ concatenation operator. I am not really convinced with the continuation idea
since I have been for years a happy user of the reactor model that's implemented
in frameworks liked Twisted. Read the <a class="reference" href="http://www.nagare.org/trac/blog">blog</a> and <a class="reference" href="http://www.nagare.org/trac/wiki">documentation</a> for more
information.</p>
<p>I had a chat with Jasper Op de Coul about Infrae's <a class="reference" href="http://wiki.europython.eu/TalkMaterials?action=AttachFile&amp;do=get&amp;target=MOAI+Server">OAI Server</a> and the work he
did to manage RDF data in Subversion and a relational database before publishing
it within a web app based on <a class="reference" href="http://developer.yahoo.com/yui/">YUI</a>. We commented code that handles books and
library catalogs. Part of my CubicWeb demo was about books in DBpedia and
<a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/project/cubicweb-book">cubicweb-book</a>. He gave me a nice link to the <a class="reference" href="http://xisbn.worldcat.org/xisbnadmin/doc/api.htm">WorldCat API</a>.</p>
<p>Souheil Chelfouh showed me his work on <a class="reference" href="http://tracker.trollfot.org/wiki/Dolmen">Dolmen</a> and Menhir. For several design
problems and framework architecture issues, we compared the solutions offered by
the <a class="reference" href="http://docs.zope.org/zopetoolkit/">Zope Toolkit</a> library with the ones found by CubicWeb. I will have to read
more about <a class="reference" href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/martian">Martian</a> and <a class="reference" href="http://grok.zope.org/">Grok</a> to make sure I understand the details of that
component architecture.</p>
<p>I had a chat with Martijn Faassen about packaging Python modules. A one sentence
summary would be that the Python community should agree on a meta-data format
that describes packages and their dependencies, then let everyone use the tool
he likes most to manage the installation and removal of software on his system.
I hope the work done during the last PyConUS and led by Tarek Ziadé arrived at the
same conclusion. Read David Cournapeau's blog entry about <a class="reference" href="http://cournape.wordpress.com/2009/04/01/python-packaging-a-few-observations-cabal-for-a-solution/">Python Packaging</a> for
a detailed explanation of why the meta-data format is the way to go. By the way,
Martijn is the lead developer of Grok and Martian.</p>
<p>Godefroid Chapelle and I talked a lot about Zope Toolkit (ZTK) and CubicWeb. We
compared the way the two frameworks deal with pluggable components. ZTK has
adapters and a registry. CubicWeb does not use adapters as ZTK does, but has a
<a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/doc/en/intro/tutorial/create-cube#defineviews">view selection mechanism</a> that required a registry with more features than the
one used in ZTK. The ZTK registry only has to match a tuple (Interface, Class)
when looking for an adapter, whereas CubicWeb's registry has to find the views
that can be applied to a result set by checking various properties:</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li>interfaces: all items of first column implement the Calendar Interface,</li>
<li>dimensions: more than one line, more than two columns,</li>
<li>types: items of first column are numbers or dates,</li>
<li>form: form contains key XYZ that has a value lower than 10,</li>
<li>session: user is authenticated,</li>
<li>etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>As for Grok and Martian, I will have to look into the details to make sure
nothing evil is hinding there. I should also find time to compare <a class="reference" href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/zope.schema">zope.schema</a>
and <a class="reference" href="http://www.logilab.org/project/yams">yams</a> and write about it on this blog.</p>
<p>And if you want more information about the conference:</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li>photos tagged europython in <a class="reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/europython/">flickr</a> and <a class="reference" href="http://www.europython.eu/gallery/europython-2009/">gallery</a> on the website</li>
<li><a class="reference" href="http://wiki.europython.eu/After">blogs</a> reporting on europython</li>
<li><a class="reference" href="http://wiki.europython.eu/RecordedTalks">recorded</a> talks and <a class="reference" href="http://wiki.europython.eu/TalkMaterials">presentation</a> materials</li>
</ul><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://www.gawel.org/weblog/fr/2007/05/journees-python-francophones-juin-2007">[gawel] Journées Python Francophones</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/8dXfwGMfuLU/9138">[logilab] Fetching book descriptions and covers</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/KOOCPO5FNf8/9853">[logilab] EuroSciPy'09 (part 1/2): The Need For Speed</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/yAy0KLWb-Vc/9827">[logilab] Logilab at OSCON 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/FMMhRpY4xNs/344349">[cubicweb] News from Europython 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/HiUtO6H72hg/9860">[logilab] The Configuration Management Problem</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/CvQCQ7Rp5bQ/343598">[cubicweb] CubicWeb for DBPedia and OpenLibrary at PyConFr'09</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/viYkOez-KvY/9579]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-10 15:12:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[carlchenet] Retour à chaud sur les RMLL 2009]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Bonjour à tous,
À peine revenu (sous la contrainte, je serais bien resté jusqu&#8217;au bout  ) des RMLL 2009, quelques mots à chaud sur cet événement :
Ma conférence a ouvert le thème &#8220;Développement&#8221; des RMLL organisé par Olivier Berger, mainteneur Debian. Malgré l&#8217;heure matinale, un public de personnes intéressées a patiemment écouté mon retour d&#8217;expérience [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=carlchenet.wordpress.com&blog=7722010&post=64&subd=carlchenet&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://carlchenet.wordpress.com/2009/07/09/retour-a-chaud-sur-les-rmll-2009/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-09 21:46:35</pubDate>
    <category>debian-fr</category>
    <category>python</category>
    <category>bélier</category>
    <category>debian</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[ccomb] Repoze.BFG sort en version 1.0, et vole la vedette à Grok]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="document">
<p>Les technologies Zope évoluent d'une manière extrêmement positive. Alors que le vieux Zope 2 survit encore après plus de dix ans de service, sa réécriture modulaire et pythonique, connue sous le nom « Zope 3 », a abouti principalement à trois choses :</p>
<blockquote>
<ul class="simple">
<li>l'Architecture de Composants (la Zope Component Architecture)</li>
<li>une multitude de composants basés sur cette architecture (la Zope Library)</li>
<li>des frameworks web utilisant cette architecture</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Parmi ces frameworks, on retrouve d'abord « Zope 3 » lui-même, qui peut s'utiliser tout seul. Puis Grok, un projet parallèle, basé sur Zope 3, qui simplifie la configuration des composants en évitant l'écriture de XML. Grok n'est pas encore sorti en version 1.0 qu'il vient de se faire griller la priorité par Repoze.BFG. BFG est un framework ultra-léger, beaucoup moins orienté Zope, plus proche de Pylons ou Django, mais quand-même basé sur l'Architecture de Composants.</p>
<p>La légèreté de Pylons ? La modularité de l'Architecture de Composants de Zope 3 ? La possibilité d'utiliser tous les middlewares WSGI ? Le choix entre modèle MVC ou modèle à la Zope ? Le menu est alléchant. Voici la traduction de l'annonce :</p>
<p>(Annonce originale : <a href="http://lists.repoze.org/pipermail/repoze-dev/2009-July/001936.html" class="reference external">http://lists.repoze.org/pipermail/repoze-dev/2009-July/001936.html</a> )</p>
<hr class="docutils" />
<div id="r-sum" class="section">
<h3>Résumé</h3>
<p>La première version majeure 1.0 du framework web BFG (ou « repoze.bfg »),
est disponible.  Les infos générales sont sur : <a href="http://bfg.repoze.org" class="reference external">http://bfg.repoze.org</a>.</p>
</div>
<div id="d-tails-en-gros" class="section">
<h3>Détails en gros</h3>
<p>BFG est un framework web en Python, basé sur WSGI.  Il s'inspire de Zope,
Pylons et Django.  Il utilise en arrière plan de nombreuses technologies de Zope.</p>
<p>BFG est une partie du projet plus général Repoze (<a href="http://repoze.org" class="reference external">http://repoze.org</a>).
Il est distributé sous une licence de type BSD (<a href="http://repoze.org/license.html" class="reference external">http://repoze.org/license.html</a>).</p>
<p>BFG 1.0 représente  l'équivalent d'une année de développement.
La première version 0.1 date de juillet 2008 et près de 80 versions pre-1.0 se sont succédé depuis cette date.
Aucune d'entre elles n'a jusqu'à présent promis de rétrocompatibilité de manière explicite.
Cependant la version 1.0, constitue le point de départ d'un gel de l'API. Les prochaines
versions de la branche 1.x garantiront cette rétrocompatibilité avec 1.0. Tout manquement
à cette règle sera considéré comme un bug.</p>
</div>
<div id="gros-d-tails" class="section">
<h3>Gros détails</h3>
<p>BFG contient des améliorations modérées et incrémentales des principes rencontrés dans les frameworks de génération précédente. Il s'efforce de rendre le développement d'applications web plus amusant, plus prédictible, et plus productif, en particulier pour les vrais projets de la vraie vie.</p>
<p>À cette fin, BFG offre les fonctionnalités suivantes :</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li>Déploiement basé sur WSGI : compatible PasteDeploy et mod_wsgi.</li>
<li>Fonctionne avec Python 2.4, 2.5 et 2.6.</li>
<li>Fonctionne sur UNIX, Windows et Google App Engine.</li>
<li>Documentation complète : 100% des fonctionnalités et de l'API est documenté</li>
<li>Ensemble impressionnant de tests unitaires.  Le paquet repoze.bfg contient 11000
lignes de code Python : 8000 lignes sont des tests unitaires servant à couvrir les 3000 lignes restantes.</li>
<li>Très économe : BFG possède une faible empreinte mémoire et ne gaspille aucun cycle processeur.</li>
<li>Ne contient pas de dépendances exagérées : installer repoze.bfg grâce à "easy_install" prend moins d'une minute.</li>
<li>Lancement rapide : une application BFG typique démarre en 1 seconde.</li>
<li>Templating XML/HTML/texte ultra-rapide grâce à Chameleon (<a href="http://chameleon.repoze.org/" class="reference external">http://chameleon.repoze.org/</a>).</li>
<li>Utilise n'importe quelle couche de persistance : SQLAlchemy, SQL brut, ZODB, CouchDB, fichiers, ou n'importe quoi d'autre correspondant aux besoins de l'application.</li>
<li>Fournit de nombreux templates de démarrage de projet. Chacun d'entre eux permet de
démarrer une application BFG correspondant à une utilisation particulière.</li>
<li>Permet, au choix, de faire correspondre une URL à du code comme avec le routage d'URL de Django ou Pylons, ou bien d'utiliser
une traversée de graphe d'objets comme avec Zope. Ceci permet aux développeurs Zope ou Pylons de retrouver leurs habitudes.</li>
<li>Offre des modes de débogage pour les erreurs courantes (vue introuvable, autorisation accordée ou refusée à tort)</li>
<li>Permet aux développeurs d'organiser leur code comme bon leur semble : le framework n'impose pas de structure d'organisation du code.</li>
<li>Permet d'écrire du code qui peut être facilement testé. BFG évite d'utiliser des structures de données propres à chaque thread, qui
nuisent à l'écriture de tests. Il fournit des outils pour simuler des composants du framework comme les templates et les vues.</li>
<li>Fournit un système d'autorisation déclaratif dépendant du contexte. Ceci empêche ou autorise l'exécution
de code par comparaison des données d'identification avec les informations d'ACL stockées par une application BFG.</li>
<li>Le comportement d'une application BFG peut être augmenté ou modifié de manière arbitraire par un développeur tiers sans aucune modification du code source original de l'application. Ceci fait de BFG un bon choix pour construire des frameworks ou des applications extensibles.</li>
<li>Les développeurs Zope et Plone se sentiront à l'aise avec la terminologie et les concepts utilisés par BFG. Ils sont en grande majorité dérivés de Zope.</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="d-tails-insoutenables" class="section">
<h3>Détails insoutenables</h3>
<p>Installation rapide :</p>
<blockquote>
easy_install -i <a href="http://dist.repoze.org/bfg/current" class="reference external">http://dist.repoze.org/bfg/current</a> repoze.bfg</blockquote>
<p>Support et information :</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://bfg.repoze.org" class="reference external">http://bfg.repoze.org</a></blockquote>
<p>Tutoriels</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://docs.repoze.org/bfg/current/#tutorials" class="reference external">http://docs.repoze.org/bfg/current/#tutorials</a></blockquote>
<p>Exemples d'applications</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://docs.repoze.org/bfg/current/#sample-applications" class="reference external">http://docs.repoze.org/bfg/current/#sample-applications</a></blockquote>
<p>Documentation détaillée (explications et API) :</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://docs.repoze.org/bfg/current" class="reference external">http://docs.repoze.org/bfg/current</a></blockquote>
<p>Bug tracker :</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://bfg.repoze.org/trac" class="reference external">http://bfg.repoze.org/trac</a></blockquote>
<p>Liste de diffusion :</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="http://lists.repoze.org/listinfo/repoze-dev" class="reference external">http://lists.repoze.org/listinfo/repoze-dev</a></blockquote>
<p>canal IRC :</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="irc://irc.freenode.net#repoze" class="reference external">irc://irc.freenode.net#repoze</a></blockquote>
<p>Repoze.bfg est principalement développé par <a href="http://agendaless.com" class="reference external">Agendaless Consulting</a> et une équipe de contributeurs.</p>
<p>Un grand merci aux personnes suivantes, sans qui cette version n'aurait pas vu le jour :</p>
<p>Malthe Borch, Carlos de la Guardia, Chris Rossi, Shane Hathaway, Tom
Moroz, Yalan Teng, Jason Lantz, Todd Koym, Jessica Geist, Hanno
Schlichting, Reed O'Brien, Sebastien Douche, Ian Bicking, Jim Fulton,
Martijn Faassen, Ben Bangert, Fernando Correa Neto, YoungKing, Rob
Miller, Wichert Akkermann, David Pratt, Mark Ramm, and Chris Perkins.</p>
</div>
</div>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://ccomb.gorfou.fr/2009/7/8/repoze-bfg-vole-la-vedette-a-grok]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-08 13:25:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[segle] Le problème Mono.]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Comme beaucoup d&#8217;utiliseurs de GNU/Linux, mon environnement de bureau est Gnome.

Depuis quelques temps, cependant, quelque chose me chagrine : de plus en plus de petites applications inclues dans Gnome sont codées en Mono, port linux compatible de la plateforme .Net de chez Microsoft. Dans la pratique, cela donne des applis codées plus facilement qu&#8217;en C [...]]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://blog.segle.org/index.php/2009/07/07/le-probleme-mono/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-07 08:44:25</pubDate>
    <category>Coups de gueule</category>
    <category>Le reste du monde libre</category>
    <category>Python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] Revue de presse python semaine 28]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Petite revue de presse sur le monde python (sans aucune prétention)]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://www.afpy.org/Members/boussard/revue_presse_python_28]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-07 01:59:15</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] Revue de presse python semaine 28]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Petite revue de presse sur le monde python (sans aucune prétention)]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://zope.afpy.org/Members/boussard/revue_presse_python_28]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-07 01:59:15</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] Le Python African Tour est au Sénégal]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Après le Maroc, le Python African Tour fera escale au Sénégal du 6 au 10 juillet 2009.]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://www.afpy.org/Members/kamon/pat-senegal]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-04 02:46:50</pubDate>
    <category>A la une</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[Afpy] Le Python African Tour est au Sénégal]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[Après le Maroc, le Python African Tour fera escale au Sénégal du 6 au 10 juillet 2009.]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://zope.afpy.org/Members/kamon/pat-senegal]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-04 02:46:50</pubDate>
    <category>A la une</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[tarek] Distutils nighlty builds]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[If you want to work (or try to find some bugs in it to help out) with the latest bleeding-edge Distutils trunk version that will be shipped with Python 2.7 and Python 3.2, you can do it now !
I am creating a nighlty build every day here now : http://nightly.ziade.org/
This distribution can be installed in [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=tarekziade.wordpress.com&blog=448161&post=850&subd=tarekziade&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/03/distutils-nighlty-builds/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-03 13:57:20</pubDate>
    <category>distutils</category>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[tarek] Dropping PEP 386 (versions comparison)]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[As you might know, we are working hard on Distutils side for Python 2.7 and 3.2 upcoming releases. The biggest work is on PEP 376, that will introduce among other things a uninstaller function and functions to query installed distributions.
The other &#8220;big&#8221; work is on PEP 345. We want to introduce a new metadata field [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=tarekziade.wordpress.com&blog=448161&post=841&subd=tarekziade&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/07/03/dropping-pep-386-versions-comparison/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-03 13:44:28</pubDate>
    <category>distutils</category>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[nsteinmetz] Couchapp : créer votre première application CouchDB (Partie 2)]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>La dernière fois, je vous ai laissé avec pas grand chose, à savoir <a href="http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/post/2009/06/27/Couchapp-%3A-cr%C3%A9er-votre-premi%C3%A8re-application-CouchDB-%28Partie-1%29">couchapp installé et une squelette d'application</a>.</p>


<p>Aujourd'hui, nous allons être nettement plus ambitieux en prenant comme prétexte une application de gestion de favoris (à la delicious, en mode mono-utilisateur). Nous allons aborder le rendu d'un document en tant que tel (aka &quot;show&quot;) et les listes de documents (aka &quot;list&quot;).</p>


<h3>Avant toute chose... couchapp !</h3>


<p>Générons notre petite application :</p>

<pre class="bash">couchapp-cloned	mycouchapp
tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ couchapp generate mycouchfav
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Generating a new CouchApp <span>in</span> /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav</pre>


<p>Et poussons notre application dans notre instance CouchDB (que vous avez démarré par ailleurs) :</p>

<pre class="bash">tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ <span>cd</span> mycouchfav/
tetram:mycouchfav nicolas$ couchapp push myfav
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Pushing CouchApp <span>in</span> /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav to design doc:
http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/myfav/_design/mycouchfav
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Visit your CouchApp here:
http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/index.html</pre>


<h3>Vinrent ensuite les documents</h3>


<p>Commençons par nous créer trois favoris depuis Futon ( <a href="http://localhost:5984/_utils/">http://localhost:5984/_utils/</a>) avec la structure suivante :</p>
<ul>
<li>title</li>
<li>url</li>
<li>description</li>
<li>tag</li>
</ul>

<p>Ci-après mon jeu d'exemple au format json :</p>

<pre class="javascript"><span>&#123;</span>
   <span>&quot;_id&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;couchdb&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;_rev&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;3-1834349775&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;title&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;CouchDB Official site&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;url&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;http://couchdb.apache.org/&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;description&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;Apache CouchDB is a distributed, fault-tolerant and schema-free document-oriented database accessible via a RESTful HTTP/JSON API&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;tag&quot;</span>: <span>&#91;</span>
       <span>&quot;couchdb&quot;</span>,
       <span>&quot;database&quot;</span>,
       <span>&quot;document&quot;</span>
   <span>&#93;</span>
<span>&#125;</span>
&nbsp;
<span>&#123;</span>
   <span>&quot;_id&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;couchdbkit&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;_rev&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;2-1087649587&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;title&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;Couchdbkit&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;description&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;Couchdbkit goal is to provide a framework for your Python application to access and manage Couchdb.&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;url&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;http://www.couchdbkit.org/&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;tag&quot;</span>: <span>&#91;</span>
       <span>&quot;couchdb&quot;</span>,
       <span>&quot;python&quot;</span>,
       <span>&quot;framework&quot;</span>
   <span>&#93;</span>
<span>&#125;</span>
&nbsp;
<span>&#123;</span>
   <span>&quot;_id&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;couchapp&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;_rev&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;2-3730993466&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;title&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;couchapp&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;description&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;Utilities to make standalone CouchDB application development simple&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;url&quot;</span>: <span>&quot;http://github.com/couchapp/couchapp/tree/master&quot;</span>,
   <span>&quot;tag&quot;</span>: <span>&#91;</span>
       <span>&quot;couchdb&quot;</span>,
       <span>&quot;python&quot;</span>,
       <span>&quot;ruby&quot;</span>
   <span>&#93;</span>
<span>&#125;</span></pre>


<pre></pre>

<h3>Tu me le montres ton document ?</h3>


<p>L'url pour accéder à un document est du type :</p>

<pre>
http://localhost:5984/&lt;nom_de_la_db&gt;/_design/&lt;nom_du_design&gt;/_show/&lt;nom_du_show&gt;/&lt;id_du_document&gt;
</pre>


<p>Dans notre cas, par ex : http://localhost:5984/<strong>myfav</strong>/_design/<strong>mycouchfav</strong>/_show/<strong>fav</strong>/<strong>couchdbkit</strong> (si je prends le favori ayant pour id &quot;couchdbkit&quot;.</p>


<p>Vous venez de déduire que mon &quot;show&quot; se nomme &quot;fav&quot;. Plus exactement, il s'agit du fichier show/fav.js avec le contenu suivant :</p>

<pre class="javascript"><span>function</span><span>&#40;</span>doc, req<span>&#41;</span> <span>&#123;</span>  
    <span>// !json templates.fav</span>
    <span>// !code vendor/couchapp/template.js</span>
    <span>// !code vendor/couchapp/path.js</span>
&nbsp;
    <span>return</span> template<span>&#40;</span>templates.<span>fav</span>, <span>&#123;</span>
        title : doc.<span>title</span>,
        url : doc.<span>url</span>,
        description : doc.<span>description</span>,
        assets : assetPath<span>&#40;</span><span>&#41;</span>,
       <span>&#125;</span>
    <span>&#41;</span>;
<span>&#125;</span></pre>


<p>Expliquons ce qu'il contient :</p>
<ul>
<li>Pour un show, la fonction js prend 2 arguments : doc et req ; ce dernier content la requête et va trouver le document associée à cette requête.</li>
<li>On initialise une variable json, qui est utilisée ensuite pour appelé le template templates/fav.html</li>
<li>On inclut ensuite 2 fichiers js fournis par couchapp</li>
<li>Le return indique que l'on va charger le fichier templates/fav.html avec 4 variables qui sont le titre (title), l'url, la description du favori, ainsi qu'une variable assets qui permet de renseigner un chemin vers différents fichiers (css, js, etc).</li>
</ul>

<p>Il nous resque plus qu'à construire le fichier templates/fav.html :</p>

<pre>
&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt; 
        &lt;title&gt;&lt;%= title %&gt;&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;header&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
        &lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&lt;%= url %&gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;%= title %&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;&lt;%= description %&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;    
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;/_utils/script/json2.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;/_utils/script/jquery.js?1.2.6&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;/_utils/script/jquery.couch.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;&lt;%= assets %&gt;/vendor/couchapp/jquery.couchapp.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</pre>


<p>Il ne nous reste plus qu'à .... et non pas visualiser votre page mais au préalable pousser vos fichiers dans votre instance CouchDB :</p>

<pre class="bash">tetram:mycouchfav nicolas$ couchapp push myfav
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Pushing CouchApp <span>in</span> /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav to design doc:
http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/myfav/_design/mycouchfav
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Visit your CouchApp here:
http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/index.html</pre>


<p>Maintenant, ouvrez votre navigateur sur l'url <a href="http://localhost:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/_show/fav/couchdbkit">http://localhost:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/_show/fav/couchdbkit</a> et vous retrouvez le contenu très sommairement présenté de votre favori avec son titre, son url et sa description.</p>


<p>En conclusion, pour afficher un document, il nous faut :</p>
<ul>
<li>Un template (ici : templates/fav.html)</li>
<li>Une fonction en javascript qui nous permet de manipuler les attributs du documents en vue de leur rendu. La fonction est de type function(doc,req). La fonction est située dans un fichier shows/nom_du_show.js (ici shows/fav.js)</li>
<li>Ne pas oublier de faire un &quot;couchapp push&quot; pour envoyer vos fichiers dans votre instance CouchDB</li>
<li>Une url du type : http://localhost:5984/&lt;nom_de_la_db&gt;/_design/&lt;nom_du_design&gt;/_show/&lt;nom_du_show&gt;/&lt;id_du_document&gt;</li>
</ul>

<h3>Et ta liste, tu me la montres aussi ?</h3>


<p>Pour les listes, c'est un peu plus complexe mais pas insurmontable <img src="http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/themes/default/smilies/smile.png" alt=":-)" class="smiley" /></p>


<p>L'url est du type :</p>

<pre>
http://localhost:5984/&lt;nom_de_la_db&gt;/_design/&lt;nom_du_design&gt;/_list/&lt;nom_de_la_liste&gt;/&lt;nom_de_la_vue&gt;?&lt;paramètres&gt;
</pre>


<p>Supposons que je veuille créer la page d'accueil de mon application, celle-ci listant tous les favoris stockés. Le nom de la liste pourrait donc tout naturellement s'appeller &quot;all&quot; et le nom de la vue &quot;favs&quot;. On pourrait imaginer avoir une liste &quot;search&quot; par ex pour afficher les résultats d'une recherche sur les favoris avec des paramètres de recherche.</p>


<p>Il faut donc bien avoir en tête qu'une liste est un moyen d'afficher une vue. Une même vue peut donc partager plusieurs listes.</p>


<p>Ex :</p>

<pre>
http://localhost:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/_list/all/favs
http://localhost:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/_list/search/favs?limit=25&amp;key=%22python%22
</pre>


<p>Commençons donc par créer notre vue, avec le fichier views/favs/map.js</p>

<pre class="javascript"><span>function</span><span>&#40;</span>doc<span>&#41;</span> <span>&#123;</span>
    emit<span>&#40;</span>doc._id, <span>&#123;</span>title: doc.<span>title</span>, description: doc.<span>description</span>, url:doc.<span>url</span> <span>&#125;</span><span>&#41;</span>   
<span>&#125;</span>;</pre>


<p>Cette fonction me renvoi tous les documents de mon instance, trié par &quot;_id&quot; et avec une série de variables (title, description, url - je ne les réexplique pas, ce sont les mêmes que précédemment).</p>


<p>Passons à notre liste : lists/all.js</p>

<pre class="javascript"><span>function</span><span>&#40;</span>head, row, req, info<span>&#41;</span> <span>&#123;</span>
  <span>// !json templates.all</span>
  <span>// !code vendor/couchapp/path.js</span>
  <span>// !code vendor/couchapp/template.js</span>
&nbsp;
  <span>return</span> respondWith<span>&#40;</span>req, <span>&#123;</span>
    html : <span>function</span><span>&#40;</span><span>&#41;</span> <span>&#123;</span>
      <span>if</span> <span>&#40;</span>head<span>&#41;</span> <span>&#123;</span>
        <span>return</span> template<span>&#40;</span>templates.<span>all</span>.<span>head</span>, <span>&#123;</span>
          assets : assetPath<span>&#40;</span><span>&#41;</span>,
        <span>&#125;</span><span>&#41;</span>;
      <span>&#125;</span> <span>else</span> <span>if</span> <span>&#40;</span>row<span>&#41;</span> <span>&#123;</span>
        <span>return</span> template<span>&#40;</span>templates.<span>all</span>.<span>row</span>, <span>&#123;</span>
          fav: row.<span>value</span>,
        <span>&#125;</span><span>&#41;</span>;
      <span>&#125;</span> <span>else</span> <span>&#123;</span>
        <span>return</span> template<span>&#40;</span>templates.<span>all</span>.<span>tail</span>, <span>&#123;</span>
            assets : assetPath<span>&#40;</span><span>&#41;</span>,
        <span>&#125;</span><span>&#41;</span>;
      <span>&#125;</span>
    <span>&#125;</span>,
  <span>&#125;</span><span>&#41;</span>
<span>&#125;</span>;</pre>


<p>La nouveauté ici tient dans la fonction qui prend différents paramètres en compte (contenus honteusement récupérés de benoitc &quot;<a href="http://benoitc.im/b/_design/blog/_show/post/20090223_lego-2-les-listes" hreflang="fr">Légo 2 : les listes</a>&quot;):</p>
<ul>
<li>head: est renseigné lorsque couchdb envoie la tête de la vue. head est un objet contenant les paramètres &quot;total-rows&quot; et &quot;offset&quot; correspondant au résultat de la vue. Cela nous permet, par exemple comme dans l'exemple ci-dessus, afficher l'entête d'une page html en chargeant un template particulier.</li>
<li>row : la ligne de la vue actuellement envoyée par CouchDB.</li>
<li>req : un objet contenant les paramètres de la requête</li>
<li>row_info : un objet contenant les infos sur la ligne en cours, sa position, quel était la ligne précendente, quelle est la première ligne de la vue.</li>
</ul>

<p>L'autre nouveauté tient dans la gestion des templates HTML :</p>
<ul>
<li>Pour head, on va charger templates/all/head.html</li>
<li>Pour chaque ligne de résultat, on va charger templates/all/row.html</li>
<li>Une fois que les résultats de la requête sont épuisés, on va charger templates/all/tail.html (qui fait donc office de voiture-balai).</li>
</ul>

<p>Contenu de templates/all/head.html :</p>

<pre>
&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;My favs&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;../../screen.css&quot; type=&quot;text/css&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h2&gt;My favs...&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h1&gt;Recently...&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;dl id=&quot;bookmarks&quot;&gt;
</pre>


<p>Contenu de templates/all/row.html :</p>

<pre>
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&lt;%= fav.url %&gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;%= fav.title %&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;&lt;%= fav.description %&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
</pre>


<p>Contenu de templates/all/tail.html :</p>

<pre>
    &lt;/dl&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;/_utils/script/json2.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;/_utils/script/jquery.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;/_utils/script/jquery.couch.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;&lt;%= assets %&gt;/vendor/couchapp/jquery.couchapp.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</pre>


<p>Il ne vous reste plus qu'à pousser vos modifications dans votre instane CouchDB (ici en mode verbeux pour bien voir ce qui est poussé) :</p>

<pre>
tetram:mycouchfav nicolas$ couchapp push -v myfav
[INFO] push lists/all.js
[INFO] push shows/fav.js
[INFO] push templates/all/head.html
[INFO] push templates/all/row.html
[INFO] push templates/all/tail.html
[INFO] push templates/fav.html
[INFO] push vendor/couchapp/_attachments/jquery.couchapp.js
[INFO] push vendor/couchapp/couchapp.js
[INFO] push vendor/couchapp/date.js
[INFO] push vendor/couchapp/path.js
[INFO] push vendor/couchapp/README.md
[INFO] push vendor/couchapp/template.js
[INFO] push views/favs/map.js
[INFO] process code macro: /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav/vendor/couchapp/template.js
[INFO] process code macro: /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav/vendor/couchapp/path.js
[INFO] process code macro: /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav/vendor/couchapp/path.js
[INFO] process code macro: /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav/vendor/couchapp/template.js
[INFO] Pushing CouchApp in /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchfav to design doc:
http://127.0.0.1:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav
[INFO] Visit your CouchApp here:
http://127.0.0.1:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/index.html
</pre>


<p>Rendez vous ensuite sur : <a href="http://localhost:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/_list/all/favs">http://localhost:5984/myfav/_design/mycouchfav/_list/all/favs</a></p>


<p>Au bout du compte, nous venons de voir pour les listes :</p>
<ul>
<li>Les listes comme moyen d'afficher une vue,</li>
<li>Cela se traduit par un fichier de vue (views/mon_de_ma_vue/map.js) et un fichier liste (lists/&lt;nom_de_ma_liste&gt;.js)</li>
<li>La liste est une fonction de type function(head, row, req, info)</li>
<li>On peut spliter les templates en head.html / row.html / tail.html</li>
<li>url de type :  http://localhost:5984/&lt;nom_de_la_db&gt;/_design/&lt;nom_du_design&gt;/_list/&lt;nom_de_la_liste&gt;/&lt;nom_de_la_vue&gt;?&lt;paramètres&gt;</li>
</ul>

<h3>Au bout de cette &quot;journée&quot;</h3>


<p>Nous avons vu aux termes des parties 1 et 2 :</p>
<ul>
<li>Comment installer couchapp et générer le squelette d'une application Couchdb</li>
<li>Jouer un peu avec Futon pour créer des enregistrements dans CouchDB (même si je ne le couvre pas directement, voir pas du tout en fait)</li>
<li>Comment afficher des documents sous forme de &quot;list/views&quot; pour une collection de documents et de &quot;show&quot; pour un document de façon unitaire</li>
</ul>

<p>Il reste encore plein de choses à voir (au moins à mon niveau) :</p>
<ul>
<li>Voir comment on peut remplacer le &quot;My favs ... &quot; dans head.html par une variable extérieure au template (facile - déjà fait mais cela rajoutait une grande quantité d&quot;infos à ce post déjà très long je pense...)</li>
<li>Mieux comprendre les &quot;!json&quot; et &quot;!code&quot;</li>
<li>Les options de tri</li>
<li>&lt;insérer votre sujet ici via un commentaire&gt;</li>
<li>...</li>
</ul>

<h3>Sources utiles</h3>


<p>Les lectures indispensables pour faire ce tutoriel :</p>
<ul>
<li>benoitc : &quot;<a href="http://benoitc.im/b/_design/blog/_show/post/20090223_lego-2-les-listes" hreflang="fr">Légo 2 : les listes</a>&quot;</li>
<li>benoitc : &quot;<a href="http://benoitc.im/b/_design/blog/_show/post/20090302_legos-3-tu-vu-comme-mon-doc-rend-bien" hreflang="fr">Légo 3 : Tu as vu comme mon doc rend bien ?</a>&quot;</li>
<li>CouchDB Wiki : &quot;<a href="http://wiki.apache.org/couchdb/Formatting_with_Show_and_List" hreflang="en">Formatting with Show and List</a>&quot;</li>
</ul>

<p>Au passage, les <a href="http://benoitc.im/b/_design/blog/_show/post/20090629_mise-jour-benoitcim-nouveautes-couchdb-couchapp" hreflang="fr">nouveautés de CouchDB / Couchapp</a> mentionnées pat Benoit sont des plus intéressantes (surtout pour les listes, plus souple/flexible a priori).</p>


<p>Merci à benoitc pour éclairer ma lanterne sur couchdb/couchapp ces derniers jours <img src="http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/themes/default/smilies/smile.png" alt=":-)" class="smiley" /></p>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/post/2009/07/03/Couchapp-%3A-cr%C3%A9er-votre-premi%C3%A8re-application-CouchDB-%28Partie-2%29]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-02 22:04:00</pubDate>
    <category>CouchDB</category>
    <category>couchapp</category>
    <category>couchdb</category>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] Fetching book descriptions and covers]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/9139?vid=download" class="align-right" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/9139?vid=download" />
<p>We recently added the <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/project/cubicweb-book">book cube</a> to our intranet in order for books available in our library to show up in the search results. Entering a couple books using the default HTML form, even with the help of copy/paste from <a class="reference" href="http://books.google.com/">Google Book</a> or <a class="reference" href="http://www.amazon.com">Amazon</a>, is boring enough to make one seek out other options.</p>
<p>As a Python and Debian user, I put the <a class="reference" href="http://packages.debian.org/source/sid/python-gdata">python-gdata</a> package on my list of options, but quickly realized that the version in Debian is not current and that the books service is not yet accessible with the python gdata client. Both problems could be easily overcome since I could update Debian's version from 1.1.1 to the latest 1.3.1 and patch it with the <a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/gdata-python-client/issues/detail?id=238">book search support</a> that will be included in the next release, but I went on exploring other options.</p>
<p>Amazon is the first answer that comes to mind when speaking of books on the net and <a class="reference" href="http://pyaws.sourceforge.net/">pyAWS</a> looks like a nice wrapper around the Amazon Web Service. The quickstart example on the home page does almost exactly what I was looking for. Trying to find a Debian package of pyAWS, I only came accross <a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/boto/">boto</a> which appears to be general purpose.</p>
<p>Registering with Amazon and Google to get a key and use their web services is doable, but one wonders why something as common as books and public libraries would have to be accessed through private companies. It turns out Wikipedia knows of <em>many</em> book <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/">catalogs</a> on the net, but I was looking for a site publishing data as RDF or part of the <a class="reference" href="http://linkeddata.org">Linked Open Data</a> initiative. I ended up with almost exactly what I needed.</p>
<p>The <a class="reference" href="http://openlibrary.org/">Open Library</a> features millions of books and covers, publicly accessible as JSON using its <a class="reference" href="http://openlibrary.org/dev/docs">API</a>. There is even a dump of the database. End of search, be happy.</p>
<p>Next step is to use this service to enhance the cubicweb-book cube by allowing a user to add a new book to its collection by simply entering a <a class="reference" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isbn">ISBN</a>. All data about the book can be fetched from the OpenLibrary, including the cover and information about the author. You can expect such a new version soon... and we will probably get a new demo of <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/">CubicWeb</a> online in the process, since all that data available as a <a class="reference" href="http://openlibrary.org/dev/docs/jsondump">dump</a> is screaming for reuse as others have already found out by making it <a class="reference" href="http://mondeca.wordpress.com/2009/01/05/openlibrary-api-rdf-wrapper-on-google-app-engine/">available as RDF</a> on AppEngine!</p><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/viYkOez-KvY/9579">[logilab] EuroPython 2009</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/CvQCQ7Rp5bQ/343598">[cubicweb] CubicWeb for DBPedia and OpenLibrary at PyConFr'09</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/8dXfwGMfuLU/9138]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-07-02 13:43:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[segle] PHP 5.3 est là, mais je ne l’attendais pas…]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[En tant que développeur, PHP est le langage que j&#8217;utilise le plus.

Au boulot, en dehors, c&#8217;est toujours PHP. PHP 5 avait apporté de nombreuses nouvelles choses pour une syntaxe pour la POO plus claire.

Mais maintenant que j&#8217;ai pu goûter à Python, à Ruby, des langages vraiment objets, puissants, à la syntaxe moins laxiste, j&#8217;ai de [...]]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://blog.segle.org/index.php/2009/06/30/php-5-3-est-la-mais-je-ne-lattendais-pas/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-30 16:40:53</pubDate>
    <category>Evènements</category>
    <category>Prog</category>
    <category>Python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[tarek] mod_ntlm in FreeBSD]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[We had to install mod_ntlm under a FreeBSD 6.4 server with a colleague, but the port for this package seems broken at least for FreeBSD 6.2 and 6.4. It just doesn&#8217;t work when it initiates an NTLM session through SMB, and it seems to be compiled without the log support so the last log you [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=tarekziade.wordpress.com&blog=448161&post=834&subd=tarekziade&ref=&feed=1" />]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://tarekziade.wordpress.com/2009/06/30/mod_ntlm-in-freebsd/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-30 13:39:27</pubDate>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[gawel] Facebook connect with python]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I've discover <a class="reference external" href="http://facebook.com">Facebook</a> <a class="reference external" href="http://developers.facebook.com/connect.php">Connect</a>. So I decide to try to use it
in a new project. It look like an easy way for new user to register in my
application.</p>
<p>The first step is to follow the <a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.developers.facebook.com/index.php/Trying_Out_Facebook_Connect">Quick start guide</a>. Then whe need to take
care of Facebook in our application.  There is already a cool python library to
play with Facebook called <a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/sciyoshi/pyfacebook/">pyfacebook</a>. So you need to install it.</p>
<p>In my project I aleady use <a class="reference external" href="http://what.repoze.org/docs/1.x/">repoze.what</a> for authentification. It just rocks. So
i decide to write an IIDentifier plugin for Facebook:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="nn">sha</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="nn">facebook</span>
<span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">webob</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">Request</span>
<span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">zope.interface</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">implements</span>
<span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">repoze.who.interfaces</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">IIdentifier</span>

<span class="n">DEFAULT_FIELDS</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="s">'uid'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'name'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'first_name'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'birthday'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'relationship_status'</span><span class="p">,</span>
                  <span class="s">'proxied_email'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'sex'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'hometown_location'</span><span class="p">,</span>
                  <span class="s">'pic'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'pic_big'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'pic_small'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'pic_square'</span><span class="p">]</span>

<span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">Params</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">dict</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">__getattr__</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">attr</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">attr</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">''</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">__html__</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nb">repr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">Facebook</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">object</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">implements</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">IIdentifier</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">__init__</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">api_key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">secret_key</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">api_key</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">api_key</span>
        <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">secret_key</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">secret_key</span>

    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">identify</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="n">req</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Request</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">)</span>

        <span class="c"># initialize the api object</span>
        <span class="n">fbapi</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">facebook</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Facebook</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">api_key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">secret_key</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c"># init pyfacebook instance</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">fbapi</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">check_session</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">req</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s">'repoze.who.fb'</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">fbapi</span>
            <span class="n">user</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">fbapi</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">users</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">getInfo</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="n">fbapi</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">uid</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="n">DEFAULT_FIELDS</span><span class="p">)[</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">]</span>

            <span class="c"># we used the proxied_email and a generated password to retriave</span>
            <span class="c"># the user from our DB</span>
            <span class="n">user</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">update</span><span class="p">(</span>
                <span class="n">login</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">user</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s">'proxied_email'</span><span class="p">],</span>
                <span class="n">email</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">user</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s">'proxied_email'</span><span class="p">],</span>
                <span class="n">password</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">sha</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'</span><span class="si">%s%s</span><span class="s">'</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fbapi</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">uid</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">secret_key</span><span class="p">))</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">hexdigest</span><span class="p">(),</span>
                <span class="p">)</span>

            <span class="c"># we store the facebook data in environ</span>
            <span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s">'repoze.who.fbuser'</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Params</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">user</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">items</span><span class="p">())</span>
            <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">user</span>

    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">remember</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">identity</span><span class="p">):</span> <span class="k">pass</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">forget</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">identity</span><span class="p">):</span> <span class="k">pass</span>
</pre></div>
<p>At the first time there is no user in our DB. So the user isn't really
connected to our interface. The trick is to use a javascript callback to show
a registration form to the user with fields pre-filled with Facebook's data.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><span class="nt">&lt;html</span> <span class="na">xmlns=</span><span class="s">&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml&quot;</span> <span class="na">xmlns:fb=</span><span class="s">&quot;http://www.facebook.com/2008/fbml&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;body&gt;</span>
   <span class="nt">&lt;script </span><span class="na">src=</span><span class="s">&quot;http://static.ak.connect.facebook.com/js/api_lib/v0.4/FeatureLoader.js.php&quot;</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&quot;text/javascript&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
   <span class="nt">&lt;/script&gt;</span>
   <span class="nt">&lt;fb:login</span><span class="na">-button</span> <span class="na">onlogin=</span><span class="s">&quot;facebook_onlogin();&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span><span class="err">&lt;</span>/fb:login-button&gt;
   <span class="nt">&lt;script </span><span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&quot;text/javascript&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
     <span class="nx">FB</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">init</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;YOUR_API_KEY_HERE&quot;</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;xd_receiver.htm&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
     <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">facebook_onlogin</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
         <span class="c">// here is the trick</span>
         <span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">location</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">href</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s1">'/register/facebook'</span><span class="o">;</span>
     <span class="p">}</span>
   <span class="nt">&lt;/script&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span> <span class="nt">&lt;/html&gt;</span>
</pre></div>
<p>When the form is submitted, you need to create the real user in your application. That's all !</p>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://www.gawel.org/weblog/en/2009/06/facebook-connect-with-python]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-29 11:04:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[nsteinmetz] Couchapp : créer votre première application CouchDB (Partie 1)]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Je continue ma découverte de CouchDB avec <a href="http://github.com/couchapp/couchapp/tree/master" hreflang="en">Couchapp</a>, logiciel qui se définit comme un ensemble d'outils pour simplifier le développement d'une application avec CouchDB.</p>


<p>Ce billet chercher à compléter / mettre à jour le billet de Benoit Chesneau : &quot;<a href="http://benoitc.org/b/_design/blog/_show/post/20090219_et-les-legos-blancs-semboiterent" hreflang="fr">Et les légos s'emboitèrent</a>&quot; que je vous conseille de lire par ailleurs.</p>


<h3>Installation de Couchapp</h3>

<pre class="bash">tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ sudo easy_install couchapp</pre>


<p>Cela vous installe couchapp 0.3.2 à ce jour.</p>


<h3>Génération du squelette de votre application</h3>

<pre class="bash">tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ couchapp generate mycouchapp
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Generating a new CouchApp <span>in</span> /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchapp</pre>


<p>Le contenu est le suivant :</p>

<pre class="bash">tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ ls mycouchapp/
_attachments	lists		vendor
lib		shows		views</pre>


<p>Pour pousser votre application dans votre instance CouchDB dans une base &quot;monapp&quot; :</p>

<pre class="bash">tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ <span>cd</span> mycouchapp/
tetram:mycouchapp nicolas$ couchapp push monapp -v
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> push vendor/couchapp/_attachments/jquery.couchapp.js
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> push vendor/couchapp/couchapp.js
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> push vendor/couchapp/date.js
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> push vendor/couchapp/path.js
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> push vendor/couchapp/README.md
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> push vendor/couchapp/template.js
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Pushing CouchApp <span>in</span> /Users/nicolas/Documents/Projets/CouchDB/mycouchapp to design doc:
http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/monapp/_design/mycouchapp
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Visit your CouchApp here:
http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/monapp/_design/mycouchapp/index.html
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Attaching index.html <span>&#40;</span><span>413</span><span>&#41;</span>
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Attaching style/main.css <span>&#40;</span><span>21</span><span>&#41;</span>
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Attaching vendor/couchapp/jquery.couchapp.js <span>&#40;</span><span>6984</span><span>&#41;</span></pre>


<p>Si vous ouvrez votre navigateur sur <a href="http://127.0.0.1:5984/monapp/_design/mycouchapp/index.html">http://127.0.0.1:5984/monapp/_design/mycouchapp/index.html</a>, vous voyez l'écran suivant :</p>


<p><img src="http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/public/Couchapp-1.png" alt="Couchapp-1.png" title="Couchapp-1.png, juin 2009" /></p>


<p>A ce stade, 2 commandes ont été utilisées :</p>
<ul>
<li>generate : crée le squelette d'application</li>
<li>push : envoie l'application dans couchdb</li>
</ul>

<p>Si vous voulez récupérer une application de couchdb, il faut utiliser la commande &quot;clone&quot;. Cela permet d'éditer votre application couchdb depuis votre disque dur et non plus depuis futon par ex. Au passage, vous ne pouvez pas cloner votre application dans le même répertoire que l'initial :</p>

<pre class="bash">tetram:mycouchapp nicolas$ <span>cd</span> ..
tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ couchapp clone http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/monapp/_design/mycouchapp
<span>&#91;</span>CRITICAL<span>&#93;</span> an app already exist here: mycouchapp</pre>


<p>Il vous faut donc spécifier un chemin différent :</p>

<pre class="bash">tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ couchapp clone http://<span>127.0</span><span>.0</span><span>.1</span>:<span>5984</span>/monapp/_design/mycouchapp mycouchapp-cloned
<span>&#91;</span>INFO<span>&#93;</span> Cloning mycouchapp to mycouchapp-cloned...
tetram:CouchDB nicolas$ ls mycouchapp-cloned/
_attachments	lib		shows		views
couchapp.json	lists		vendor</pre>


<p>A noter que la version clonée a un fichier couchapp.json en plus et donc je ne connais pas encore l'intérêt / l'utilité à ce stade.</p>


<p>Si on revient un instant sur ces répertoires :</p>
<ul>
<li>_attachments contiendra les fichiers attachés à votre application</li>
<li>views contient les vues</li>
<li>lists contient les listes de vues ; utilisées par ex pour une page listant les 10 derniers documents par ex style page d'accueil d'un blog.</li>
<li>shows contient les rendus d'un document ; la visualisation d'un article d'un blog par ex.</li>
<li>lib contient les modèles et macros</li>
<li>vendor contient des composants tiers fournis par couchapp pour le moment mais on peut imaginer je suppose d'autres briques tierces dans cet espace .</li>
</ul>

<p>Voilà pour un début, dès que je suis plus clair sur les listes / vues / rendus, vous aurez droit à un autre billet <img src="http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/themes/default/smilies/smile.png" alt=":-)" class="smiley" /></p>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://nicolas.steinmetz.fr/journal/post/2009/06/27/Couchapp-%3A-cr%C3%A9er-votre-premi%C3%A8re-application-CouchDB-%28Partie-1%29]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-27 14:19:00</pubDate>
    <category>CouchDB</category>
    <category>couchapp</category>
    <category>couchdb</category>
    <category>python</category>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] What's new in cubicweb 3.3]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>After the CubicWeb 3.2 blackout, the release early, release often
mantra strikes back and <a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/project/cubicweb/3.3.0">CubicWeb 3.3</a> is out ! A few bugs were
fixed, mainly migration scripts bug, and some new functionalities were
added among which the long awaited standard plotting feature. We've
added piechart support (with <cite>gchartwrapper</cite>) and standard plots with
<a class="reference" href="http://code.google.com/p/flot/">flot</a>.</p>
<img align="right" alt="under creative commons by jared" class="align-right" src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1223/943077854_b1424ef6e5_m_d.jpg" />
<div class="section" id="features">
<h3><a>Features</a></h3>
<ul class="simple">
<li>jquery has been updated to the latest 1.3.x version</li>
<li>plotting facilities using Flot and Google Chart have been added
(replacing sometimes similar facilities using matplotlib)</li>
<li>the i18n command names have been changed</li>
<li>also a non-negligible amount of internal refactorings occurred, but
this should be quite transparent</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="section" id="bugs-fixed">
<h3><a>Bugs fixed</a></h3>
<ul class="simple">
<li>problems with migrations using SQL has been fixed</li>
<li>bugs with the multi-source planner have been fixed</li>
<li>problems with synchronize-schema and not-null constraints</li>
</ul>
<p><em>photo licenced under</em> <a class="reference" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CreativeCommons</a> <em>by</em> <a class="reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/generated/">jared</a></p>
</div><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/gXszEZohedA/343505">[cubicweb] Cubicweb 3.2 : what's new</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/TMBthnk-_nI/8813">[logilab] Pylint at BayPIGgies</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/-7Uhh173ji8/253861">[cubicweb] Using email with CubicWeb</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/6ACRDiUaPJw/241763">[cubicweb] Migration in Python Web Frameworks ORMs</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/OdekJW8n-yU/344026]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-24 20:11:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] Semantic web technology conference 2009]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<div><img align="left" src="http://image.bio-medicine.org/img/Fifth-Annual-SemTech-Conference-Highlights-How-Semantics-Power-Chemistry--Pharmaceutical--Healthcare--and-Other-Life-Science-Solutions.gif" /><a href="http://semtech2009.com/">The semantic web technology conference</a> is taking place every year in San Jose, California. It is meant to be the world's symposium on the business of semantic technologies. Essentially here we discuss about semantic search, how to improve access to the data and how we make sense of structured, but mainly unstructured content.&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
Some exhibitors were more NLP oriented, concepts extraction (such as <a href="http://www.semanticv.com/">SemanticV</a>), others were more focused on providing a scalable storage (essentially RDF storage). Most of the solutions includes a data aggregator/unifier in order to combine multi-sources data into a single storage from which ontologies could be defined. &#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
Then on top of that is the enhanced search engine. They concentrate on internal data within the enterprise and not that much about using the Web as a resource. For those who built a web application on top of the data, they choosed <a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/flex/">Flex</a> as their framework (<a href="http://www.metatomix.com/">Metatomix</a>).</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div>From all the exhibitors, the ones that kept my attention were <a href="http://www.cambridgesemantics.com/products/anzo_on_the_web">The Anzo suite</a> (<a href="http://www.openanzo.org/">open source project</a>), <a href="http://ordi.sourceforge.net/">ORDI</a> and <a href="http://www.franz.com/agraph/allegrograph/">Allegrograph RDF store</a>.</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div>Developped by Cambridge Semantics, in Java, Anzo suite, especially, Anzo on the web and Anzo collaboration server, is the closest tools to CubicWeb, providing a multi source data server and an AJAX/HTML interface to develop semantic web applications, customize views of the data using a templating language. It is available in open source.&#13;&#13;&#13;
The feature that I think was interesting is an assistant to load data into their application that then helps the users define the data model based on that data. The internal representation of the content is totally transparent to the user, types are inferred by the application, as well as relations.</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div><img src="http://www.w3.org/RDF/icons/rdf_w3c_icon.96.gif" alt="RDF Resource Description Framework Icon" align="right" />I did not get a demo of ORDI, but it was just mentionned to me as an open source equivalent to CubicWeb, which I am not too sure about after looking at their web site. It does data integration into RDF.</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div>Allegrograph RDF store is a potential candidate for another source type in CubicWeb . It is already supported by Jena and Sesame framework. &#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
They developped a Python client API to attract pythonist in the Java world. </div>&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div>They all agreed on one thing : the use of SPARQL should be the standard query language. I quickly heard about Knowledge Interface Format (KIF) which seems to be an interesting representation of knowledge used for multi-lingual applications. If there was one buzz word to recall from the conference, I would choose ontology :)</div>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/o67WJnJ0SmI/9374]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-22 11:15:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[cubicweb] Cubicweb 3.2 : what's new]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" alt="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3045/2585844966_05f617cd92_m.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3045/2585844966_05f617cd92_m.jpg" />
<p>Cubicweb has experienced a rather large shakeup. Some things needed
major restructuration, and that is why you have been left with few
releases in the past few weeks. All the cubes available at
<a class="reference" href="http://www.cubicweb.org/project">http://www.cubicweb.org/project</a> have been updated accordingly.</p>
<p>Version 3.2 brings us considerable improvements for:</p>
<div class="section" id="form-construction">
<h3><a>Form construction</a></h3>
<p>Cubicweb has had for long a nice system of forms smart enough to build
themselves out of one cube's schema and some programmer-provided hints
(or 'relation tags') to fine-tune things.</p>
<p>It was not easy however to customize these forms nor to build new ones
from scratch.</p>
<p>So the new form systems draws from django-forms flexibility and style,
keeping all the automatic goodness, and also make it quite easy now to
build or customize forms at will.</p>
<p>This is the area were backwards compatibility is mostly gone. Custom
forms will have to be rewritten. Don't be angry about that, the forms
overhaul was long overdue, and from now it will only move in small
evolutionary, well-mannered steps.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="relation-tags">
<h3><a>Relation tags</a></h3>
<p>Along with the form subsystem is the __rtags__ mechanism substantially
updated and made more extensible. The __rtags__ were quite incorrectly
attached to entities class at the ORM level instead of being related
to views and forms. The cubicweb.web.uicfg module now provides a
comprehensive catalog of relation tags instances allowing automatic
forms and views customisation in a nicely declarative manner.</p>
<p>Cubicweb 3.2 still remains compatible with the old __rtags__.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="view-selection-filtering">
<h3><a>View selection/filtering</a></h3>
<p>Cubiweb has also had for long a nice mechanism to filter views
applicable to a given result set, the selector system. Various
base classes were provided to hide selectors from the
programmer and it had grown a little messy.</p>
<p>Selectors now have a nicer declarative feeling and the framework does
not try to hide them. Quite the opposite: writing, maintaining and
using selectors is now a breeze, and the base classes are gone. More
is less !</p>
<p>However Cubicweb 3.2 remains backward compatible with the old
selectors. Runtime warnings will help you track these and adapt as you
see fit.</p>
</div>
<div class="section" id="other-features">
<h3><a>Other features</a></h3>
<p>On the smaller features side, worth mentioning are:</p>
<ul class="simple">
<li>new RichString attribute type in schema definitions, that simplifies
format and encoding management,</li>
<li>inline relation edition is now possible (it was formerly limited to
attributes) with 'reledit' view,</li>
<li>workflow definition has been simplified,</li>
<li>web/views has been somewhat cleanup up and reorganized,</li>
<li>automatic registration of app objects can now be switched to manual
mode (no more hairy hard-to-debug registerer mechanism),</li>
<li>a generic SIOC view,</li>
<li>a view synthetizing permissions across a whole app.</li>
</ul>
<p>We hope you enjoy this release!
The cubicweb development team.</p>
<p><em>photo by</em> <a class="reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/people/generated/">jared</a> <em>under</em> <a class="reference" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">creative commons</a></p>
</div><br/><br/>
<div>
  <strong>Related</strong>
  <ul>
         <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/OdekJW8n-yU/344026">[cubicweb] What's new in cubicweb 3.3</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/TMBthnk-_nI/8813">[logilab] Pylint at BayPIGgies</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/-7Uhh173ji8/253861">[cubicweb] Using email with CubicWeb</a></li>

     <li><a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/6ACRDiUaPJw/241763">[cubicweb] Migration in Python Web Frameworks ORMs</a></li>

  </ul>
</div>
]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/cubicweborg/~3/gXszEZohedA/343505]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-18 19:43:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] Emacs and mercurial trick]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="left" alt="http://www.logilab.org/image/8863?vid=download" class="align-left" src="http://www.logilab.org/image/8863?vid=download" />
<p>While using emacs I always find the need to use grep on a terminal to search for things within
a specific project. This is not ideal, even within an embedded emacs shell.</p>
<p>Since I recently discovered the emacs command <tt class="docutils literal"><span class="pre">grep-find</span></tt>  I decided to make it work nicely
with mercurial projects, and here's the result:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">defun</span> <span class="n">grep</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">project</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">s</span><span class="o">)</span>
  <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">interactive</span> <span class="s2">&quot;sSearch project for: &quot;</span><span class="o">)</span>
   <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">grep</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">find</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">concat</span> <span class="s2">&quot;files=(`hg manifest`);grep -nH -e </span><span class="se">\&quot;</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span> <span class="n">s</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="se">\&quot;</span><span class="s2"> ${files[@]/#/`hg root`/}&quot;</span><span class="o">))</span>
<span class="o">)</span>
<span class="o">(</span><span class="n">global</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">set</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">key</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">quote</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="n">f4</span><span class="o">])</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">quote</span> <span class="n">grep</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">project</span><span class="o">))</span>
</pre></div>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/7tQHLPZc7qg/8860]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-17 21:20:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[logilab] Google I/O 2009]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[<img align="right" src="http://code.google.com/intl/fr/apis/wave/images/wavelogo.png" /><div>The big event of the conference was the annoucement of <a href="http://wave.google.com/">Google Wave</a>, a new online communication and collaboration tool, built on the Google Web Toolkit (GWT).&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
Another big thing the GWT, lots of application built with it, a delightful tool for Java developers.</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div>It was interesting to see that Google App Engine (GAE) will shortly provide an API to do offline processing, with objects called Task Queue. &#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
Task queue are web hooks, tasks are pushed to the server, queued and they are pushed until the task is executed (which overpass the annoying well-known time out issue with Google App Engine). &#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
It was introduced as asynchronous, enabling low latency, reliable and scalable (where are the buzz words?).&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
Of course, this news has been a huge relief for most of the developers in the public as that was a big missing part from GAE.</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div>An nice presentation from the founders of FrontSeat.org about their current project <a href="http://www.walkscore.com">Walk score</a>. They introduced themselves as civic software developers, writing software in a civic manner.&#13;&#13;
They explained how they use GAE, and why they had to use Amazon EC2 to compensate GAE gaps. The gaps they listed here were the ranking non-ability of GAE, the too long reponse time for such computation they do, the fact that no cron jobs can be done (the arrival of Task Queue might change their opinion).</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
<img src="http://code.google.com/intl/fr/events/io/images/io2009.png" align="left" /><div>All the sessions have been recorded and are available <a href="http://code.google.com/events/io/sessions.html">here</a>.</div>&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
&#13;&#13;&#13;&#13;
<div>And yes, as all the participants of this conference, I went back home with an Android phone :)</div>]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/logilaborg/~3/obj3oPlSE0U/9322]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-10 11:05:00</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title><![CDATA[[segle] Python (entre autres) sur Android !]]></title>
    <description><![CDATA[J&#8217;en ai rêvé, google l&#8217;a fait.

Ca s&#8217;appelle Android Scripting Environment, ça a accès (selon leurs dires) à la plus grosse partie des API pour faire mumuse avec le système, et ça supporte Python, Lua, BeanShell, et en prévision Ruby et Javascript (sisi).

Et tout ça sous Apache Public Licence.

Je plonge là-dedans dès que possible !

Edit : [...]]]></description>
    <link><![CDATA[http://blog.segle.org/index.php/2009/06/09/python-entre-autres-sur-android/]]></link>
    <pubDate>2009-06-09 14:30:24</pubDate>
    <category>Prog</category>
    <category>Python</category>
    <category>android</category>
  </item>
</channel>
</rss>

